In it you will see Dr. Gibbs,
Mrs. Gibbs, George Gibbs, Rebecca Gibbs,
Constable Warren, Howie Newsome,
Joe Crowell, Si Crowell, Simon Stinson, Mrs. Soames.
The name of our town is Grover’s Corners,
New Hampshire
The first act shows a day in our town.
The date is May 7, 1901,
Sky is showing some streaks of light
over in the East there,
the mornin’ star gets brighter
just before it has to go.
Over there on the left is the railroad tracks.
The Congregational Church is over there;
the Presbyterian’s across the street.
Methodist and Unitarian are over there.
Baptist is—by the river.
Across the tracks is—
the Catholic Church,
Next to the Post Office is the
Town Hall; jail is in the basement.
Washington once made a speech
This is the Main Street.
Here are the poles that the horses are tied to.
First automobile’s goin’ to come
along in about five years—
belonged to Banker Cartwright,
our richest citizen.
Lives in the big white house
on the hill.
Here’s the grocery store
and Mr. Morgan’s drugstore.
Everyone in town goes
to those stores.
This is Doctor Gibbs’ house.
This is the back door.
Here’s a couple of trellises
for those who need scenery.
This is Mrs. Gibbs’ garden— Corn…
chickpeas... beans... peas... heliotrop
and lots of weeds.
Back then we got newspapers
twice a week—
the Grover’s Corners Sentinel—
this is Editor Webb’s house
Corn…
is a big walnut tree.
Nice town, right?
Nobody very remarkable
ever come out of it.
The earliest dates on
the tombstones in the cemetery
say 1670–1680. They’re Grovers
and Cartwrights
and Gibbses and Herseys—-
same names from here now.
Like I said: it’s early morning.
The only lights on are in a cottage
over by the tracks where
a Polish mother’s had twins.
And in the Joe Crowell house,
where Joe Junior’s gettin’ ready
to deliver the paper.
And in the depot, where Shorty Hawkins
is gettin’ ready
But town folks sleep late.
So—another day’s begun.
Mrs. Gibbs died of pneumonia
visiting her daughter Rebecca,
who married an insurance man
in Canton, Ohio,
She’s buried in that cemetery—
in the Congregational Church.
In our town we like to know
the facts about everybody.
There’s Mrs. Webb
And here comes Joe Crowell
deliverin' the paper.
Anybody been sick?
No. Some twins born
in Polish Town —
I see your teacher Miss Foster
is getting married.
Yes, sir, to a man in Concord.
Well, how do you boys
feel about that?
Well, it’s not my business—
How’s your knee, Joe?
when it’s going to rain.
I want to tell you something about that boy.
Joe was smart—
graduated top of his class.
He got a scholarship to Boston
Tech—M.I.T.
Graduated top of his class from there too.
It was in all the Boston papers
at the time.
Joe was going to be an engineering,
but the war started
and he died in France.
All that education for nothing.
What business he had fighting the Germans
we don’t know now, but it seemed
perfectly clear at the time.
Here comes Howie Newsome
delivering milk.
Giddy up, Bessie.
What’s the matter with you?
Going to rain, Howie?
No. Fine day,
with sunshine,
Hello, Bessie!
How old is she?
cancelled their milk delivery.
She wants to head that way
and yells at me
the whole time.
Doc
Is he? Seems like
you’re late today.
Aya. Something went wrong with the cart this morning.
Children, time to get up!
Come on, Bessie!
Everything ok, Frank?
Yes. Easy as kittens.
Bacon will be ready soon.
Come drink your coffee.
Can you get some more sleep
this morning?
Mrs. Wentworth’s cornin’ at
eleven with a stomach issue.
I know what’s her problem.
Her stomach is not the same as it was.
You won’t get more than three hours sleep.
Frank Gibbs, I don't know
what’s goin’ to become of you.
I  wish you could rest more.
It would do you good.
Emily!
You’ve got to speak to George.
I can’t even get him
to cut me wood.
Is he sassy to you?
No, just whines!
All he thinks about is baseball—
George! Rebecca!
You’ll be late for school.
George! George, look sharp!
I’m going to lie down.
Wash yourself good
or I’ll do it myself.
Ma! What dress shall I wear?
I washed and ironed your blue dress.
Mama, George’s throwin’ soap at me!
We got a factory in our town, too.
Makes blankets. Cartwrights own it,
made  a fortune.
Children! Now slow down.
Breakfast is just as important as lunch or dinner.
I won’t have you gobblin’ like wolves.
Oh, Ma! By ten o’clock I got to know
about Canada.
You know the rules —
no books at table.
I’d rather have my children
I’m both, Mama,
you know I am.
I’m the brightest girl in school my age.
I have a very good memory.
Eat your breakfast.
I’ll speak to your father.
Twenty-five cents a week’s enough
for a boy of your age.
I don’t know how you spend it all.
Aw, Ma,—I gotta lotta
things to buy.
Strawberry phosphates—
that’s what you spend it on.
I don’t see why Rebecca gets much
money. She has more  than a dollar.
I’ve been saving up.
Well, I think it’s good to spend
some every now an’ then.
Mama, you know what I love most
in the world? Money.
There's the bell. I gotta go.
Don’t run.
Wally, pull up your pants.
Rebecca,
Yes, Ma.
You look nice, Rebecca.
Pick up your feet!
Here, here— No, you go away,— Here—
What's the matter with you?
All you do is fight— You don’t belong
to me. Where'd you come from?
Good morning, Myrtle.
How’s your cold?
Well, I still have a tickle in my throat.
Told Charles I didn’t know
if I’d go to choir rehearsal tonight.
Have you tried singing
Yes, but I can’t stay on key.
While I’m restin' I thought
I’d string some beans.
Let me help.
Beans have been good this year.
Aya, I want to have forty quarts if it
kills me. Children say they hate ’em
but they’ll eat them
all winter.
Look,
Myrtle, I have to tell you something.
Why Julia Gibbs!
Tell me, Myrtle,
is one of those
second-hand furniture men
come to see you?
No
Well, he visited me.
First I thought he was
one of Doctor Gibbs’ patients.
He came inside
and offered me 350 dollars
for Grandmother Wentworth's highboy.
Why, Julia Gibbs!
Yes, yes. On that old thing.
It was so big
I almost give it to my cousin,
Hester Wilcox
You don’t know!—three hundred and
fifty dollars? What’s come over you?
If I could get my husband
I’d sell it like that.
You know, Myrtil,
I’ve always wanted to see
I’ve been promising myself for years
that if we ever had the chance-—
How’s Doctor feel about it?
Well, I said if I got
an inheritance—
that’s the way I put it—
I’d make him take me.
M-m-m— What did he say?
You know how he is. I haven’t heard a serious
word out of him, since I’ve known him.
No, he said, it might
make him discontented
with Grover’s Corners
to go to Europe;
Every two years he makes a trip
to the battlefields of the Civil War
and that’s enough he says.
Mr. Webb’s ready to give up Napoleon
and move over to the Civil War
only Doctor Gibbs being one of the greatest
experts in the country makes him despair.
It’s a fact,
my husband
The times I’ve walked over those hills,
Myrtle, stopping at every bush,
like we was going to buy it.
Well, if that second-hand man’s
serious Julia, you sell it.
And then you’ll get to see Paris.
Just keep droppin’ hints —
Oh, I’m sorry I mentioned it.
Only it seems to me that once in your life,
you ought to see a country where
they don’t talk in English
and don’t even want to.
Thank you very much, ladies.
But first we want a little more information
about our town— a scientific account.
So I’ve asked Professor Willard of our
State University to discuss
our past history here.
Professor Willard?
May I introduce Professor Willard
Just a few brief notes, —
unfortunately our time is limited.
Grover’s Corners—mmm— let me see—
Grover's Corners lies
on the old pleiocene granite
of the Appalachian range
on some of the oldest land
in the world—
we’re proud of that. Of course there are more recent
outcroppings,—sandstone showing
through a shelf of Devonian basalt,
and some vestiges of Mezozoic shale,
but these are comparatively new—
perhaps two or three hundred million years.
Some interesting fossils
have been found—
two miles north of the Peckham Farm—
in Silas Peckham’s cow-pasture.
These may be seen in the museum at
the University at any reasonable time.
Shall I read some of
Professor Gruber’s notes
on the meteorological situation—
mean precipitation, et cetera?
Afraid we won’t have time for that,
Professor.
We might have a few words
on the history of man here.
Early Amerindian stock,
Cotahatchee tribes—
no evidence before
the 10th Century —
now entirely disappeared—
Oh, possible traces in three families—
migration in early part
of the 17th Century
of English brachiocephalic
blue-eyed stock—
Since then, some Slav
and Mediterranean—
And the population?
Oh yes. The population
at the moment is 2,642.
The Postal District brings in 507 more—
making a total of 3,149.
Mortality, birth rates—constant.
By McPherson’s gauge: 6.032.
Thank you very much,
Professor Willard.
We are all truly obliged to you.
Now the political and social report:
Oh, Mr. Webb?
He’ll be here soon—
He just cut his hand eatin’ an apple.
All males vote at the age of 21.
Women vote indirect.
We’re lower middle-class:
sprinklin’ of professional men—
and
10% illiterate laborers: unskilled,
Politically,
86% Republicans;
6% Democrats; 4% Socialists;
Rest, indifferent.
Religiously, 85% Protestants;
12% Catholics;
Rest, indifferent.
Have you any comments,
Mr. Webb?
What do you think of our little town,
Grovers Corner’s, Mr Webb?
Well, if you ask me, I can tell you
that it
Little better behaved
than most.
Probably a lot duller. But our young people here
seem to like it well enough
90% of ’em settle down right here
to live—
even when they’ve-been away to college.
Is there much drinking in Grover’s Corners?
Well, ma’am, I wouldn’t know
what you’d call much.
Saturday nights the farmhands meet
down in Ellery Greenough’s stable.
We’ve got one or two town drunks.
But they always repent whenever
a travelling preacher comes to town.
No, I’d say liquor
ain’t a regular thing in the home here,
except as medicine for a cold.
Or snake-bite, y
This has always been like that.
The next question is about social issues
and social injustice.
Why doesn't anyone do something about it?
Everybody is,—somethin’ terrible.
most of their time talking about
who’s rich and who’s poor.
Well, I dunno. I guess
we’re huntin’
for a way the diligent and sensible
can rise to the top
and the lazy and quarrelsome
sink to the bottom.
But it ain’t easy to find.
Meantime, we take care of those
who can’t help themselves
and those that can we leave alone.
Any other questions?
I
Well, ma’am, there ain't much—not in the sense
you mean. There’s some girls
that play the piano over at High School
Commencement; but they ain’t happy about it.
There isn’t much culture;
but we like the sun cornin’ up
over the mountain in the morning, and we all
notice a good deal about the birds.
And we watch the change
of the seasons:
yes, everybody knows about them.
But those other things—
there ain’t much—Robinson Crusoe
and the Bible;
those are about as far as we go.
Now we’ll go back to town.
All
The children have gone back to school.
Doc
tor
Mr. Webb’s cuttin’
his lawn —
one man in ten thinks it’s a privilege
to push his own lawn-mower.
I can’t, Lois.
I’ve got to go help my mother.
I promised her.
Emily, walk simply.
Who do you think you are today?
Oh, Papa, one minute you tell me
to stand up straight
and the next minute you call me names.
I don’t listen to you.
Sorry, Mrs. Forrest…
Hello, Emily!
H
You made a fine speech in class.
Well—I was ready to make a speech
about the Monroe Doctrine,
but at the last minute
Miss Corcoran made me
talk about the Louisiana Purchase.
I worked hard on both of them.
Gee, it’s funny, Emily.
From my window I can see your head
nights when you’re doing your
home-work in your room.
Why, can you?
You stick to it, Emily.
I don’t see how you can sit still that long.
Well, I always feel it’s something
you have to go through.
Yeah.
Emily, what do you think?
We might work out a kinda telegraph
from your window to mine;
once in a while you could give me
hint about one of those Algebra problems.
I don’t mean the answers,
Oh I think hints are allowed.
So…
If you get stuck, you whistle
Emily, you’re naturally bright
I figure it’s just the way a person’s bom.
Yeah. But I want to be a farmer.
My Uncle Luke says
whenever I’m ready I can come work
on his farm
and if I’m any good
I can gradually have it.
You mean the house and everything?
Thanks for the talk, Emily.—
Good-afternoon, Mrs. Webb.
Emily, come help me string
these beans.
George Gibbs let himself have
a real conversation, didn’t he?
Why, he's growing up.
How old is he?
Oh, I don’t know.
Mama, I made a speech in class
today and I was very good.
You must recite it to your father at supper.
What was it about ?
The Louisiana Purchase.
It was like silk off a spool.
I’m going to make speeches all my life. —
Mama, are these big enough ?
Mama, can I ask you
something
Seriously, dear—not serious.
Mama, am I
Yes, of course. Both my children got good features.
I’d be ashamed if they hadn’t.
Oh, Mama, that’s not what I mean.
What I mean is:
I’ve already told you, yes.
You have a nice young pretty face.
Now that's enough.
Oh, Mama, you never tell us
the truth about anything.
I am telling you the truth.
Mama, were you
But Mama, you’ve got to say
something about me.
Am I pretty enough
to get people interested in me ?
You’re pretty enough for
all normal purposes.
Come along and bring
that bowl with you.
Oh, Mama, you’re no help.
Now, I think this is a good time
to tell you
that the Cartwrights have begun building
a new bank in Grover's Corners—
had to go to Vermont
for the marble.
And they've asked a friend of mine
what they should put in the cornerstone
for people to dig up
a thousand years from now.
and a copy of Mr. Webb’s Sentinel,
all that reading matter with a kind of glue—-
silicate glue—
that'll make it keep a thousand—
two thousand years—
We’
and a copy
of William Shakespeare’s plays.
Y’ know, Babylon once had
two million people in it,
and all we know about them is
the names of the kings and some copies
of wheat contracts and—
the sales of slaves.
Yes, every night all those families
sat down to supper,
and the father came home from work,
and the smoke went up the chimney, same as here.
So I’m going to have
a copy of this play
put in the cornerstone so people a thousand
years from now’ll know
about us—
more
Well then, people living
a thousand years from now
This is the way we were,
in our growing up and in our marrying,
and in our living, and in our dying.
Now we’ll get back to Grover's Corners.
It’s evening.
You can hear the choir practice
in the Congregational Church.
The children are doing their homework.
The day is runnin’ down like a tired clock.
Let’s try it again!
Bles
the fellowship of kindred minds
is like to that above.
Softer! Softer!
Get it out of your head that music’s
only good when it’s loud.
You leave loudness to the Methodists.
You can't beat them at that,
even if you wanted to.
Now again, tenors!
I can’t work.
The moonlight’s terrible.
The third.
Why, yes, George—
that’s the easiest one.
I’ll tell you one thing:
the answer’s in yards.
Oh, I see. Square yards of wall-paper!
If you hold your breath, you can hear
the train all the way to Contookuck!
Hear it?
M-m-m— What do you know!
Before I forget:
How many of you can sing
at Fred Hersey’s wedding on Tuesday?
Put your hands up.
"Art thou weary, art thou languid?"
It’s a question. Make it talk.
Ready?
Make yourself comfortable. I’ll only keep you
Me? I'm sixteen,
almost seventeen.
What do you want to do
after school’s over?
I want to be a farmer
on Uncle Luke’s farm.
You’ll be willing to get up early
and milk and feed the stock—
and you’ll hoe and hay all day ?
Sure, I will. What do you mean, Pa?
Well, George, while I was
in my office today
I heard a funny sound:
a
There you see your mother—
up early;
cooking meals all day;
washing and ironing;—
and still she has
to chop wood,
I guess she got
tired of asking you.
She decided it was easier
to do it herself.
And you eat her meals,
and put on the clothes she washes,
and you run off and play baseball,—
Well, I wanted to let you know.
Here's a handkerchief, son.
25 cents a week.
Not for chopping wood,
because that’s a present you give your mother,
but because you’re getting older—
I imagine there are things
you need it for now.
Thanks, Pa.
Let’s see—
tomorrow’s pay day.
Probably Rebecca’ll feel she ought
to have some more too.
Wonder what could
have happened to your mother.
Choir practice never was
as late as this before.
It's only half-past eight, Pa.
I don’t know why she's in that choir anyway.
She sounds like an old crow!
And traipsin’ around at this hour of the night!
About time you retired, don’t you think?
Yes, Pa.
I’ll tell Mr. Webb; I know he’ll want
to put it in the paper.
My, it’s late!
Goodnight, Irma.
Myrtle Webb! Look at that moon!
Good potato-growing weather is coming,
that’s for sure!
Well, I didn't want to say it in front of those
others but now we’re alone—,
it’s the worst scandal ever in this town!
Now, Louella!
But, Julia! The organist of a church,
drunk year after year.
You saw he was drunk tonight.
You know he was drunk tonight.
and Doctor Ferguson knows too.
A
th
Not to notice it!
But it’s getting worse.
No, it isn’t, Louella.
I’ve been in that choir twice as long as you.
It doesn’t happen anywhere near so often.
Louella, look at that beautiful moon!
Those children will be up all night.
Goodnight, Louella.
Goodnight, Myrtle.
Can you get home safe, Louella?
Oh, it’s bright as day. I can see
You’d think we’d been to a dance
the way the men folk carry on. Goodnight, Julia.
Goodnight, Louella.
Well, we had a real good time.
You’re late enough.
Why, Frank, it ain’t any later than usual.
And you stopping to gossip
with a lot of hens.
Don’t be grouchy.
Come smell
my heliotrope
Isn’t that wonderful?
What did you do tonight?
Oh, I read—What were the girls
gossiping about tonight?
Worst I've seen him.
How’ll that end, Frank?
Reverend
Ferguson
I guess I know more about Simon Stimson’s
affairs than anybody in this town.
Some people ain’t made for
small town life.
No, not yet. —Frank,
I'm worried about you.
What are you worried about ?
I think you need a real rest
and change.
If I get that inheritance.
I’m going to insist on it.
Now, Julia, not that again.
Come on, Julia, it’s late.
You’ll catch cold—
You'll have your wood chopped,
for a while anyway. No, no.
Oh dear, there’s always so many
things to pick up.
All those people that
part of town do.
They’re all gettin’ citified.
They haven't got anythin’ fit to steal..
Get out, Rebecca.
There’s only room for one here.
Well, let me look just a minute.
Use your own window.
There's no moon there
George, do you know what I think?
I think maybe the moon’s getting
nearer and nearer
and there’ll be a big explosio
You have no idea,
Rebecca
the men that sit up all night
with telescopes would see it
and it’d be in
all the newspapers.
and half the whole world?
Well—probably is.
Nine-thirty.
Most lights in town are out.
Here comes Editor Webb, after putting
his newspaper to bed.
All quiet tonight?
Simon Stimson is rollin’ around a little.
Just saw his wife out
looking for him so I looked the other way—
there he is now.
Good evening, Simon
Town seems to have settled down
for the night.
Yes, most of the people in town
have gone home, Simon.
I guess we better do the same.
Can I walk along with you?
Good night.
I don’t know how that’s goin’
to end, Mr. Webb.
Well, he's been trouble
Oh, Bill
give him a word?
He thinks a lot of you.
I don’t think he smokes,
Mr.Webb,
Hm. I hope not.
Good night, Bill.
Good night, Mr. Webb.
Why aren’t you in bed?
I don’t know. I can’t sleep, Papa.
The moonlight’s wonderful.
And Mrs. Gibbs’s heliotropes.
Can you smell it?
Hm—Yes. No troubles on your mind,
Emily?
Troubles, Papa. No
Well, don’t let your mother catch you.
Good night, Emily.
Good night
I never told you about that letter
Jane Crofut got from her minister
when she was sick.
The address on the envelope said:
Jane Crofut; The Crofut Farm,
Grover’s Corners; Sutton County;
New Hampshire;
United States of America.
What’s funny about that?
Listen, it’s not finished: the United States
of America; Continent of North America;
Western Hemisphere; the Earth;
the Solar System;
What do you know!
T
Yes, the sun has risen a thousan
Summers and winters have cracked
the mountains more
brought down some of the dirt.
Some babies that weren’t even born before,
have begun talkin’ sentences;
and a number of people who thought
they were young have noticed
that they can’t bound up a flight
of stairs like they used to.
All that can happen
in a thousand days.
Nature’s been pushin’ in
other ways, too—
a number of young people fell in love.
In our town there aren’t
many exceptions.
Most everybody climbs
into their grave married.
So; three years later. 1904.
July 7th,
just after High School Commencement.
That’s when our young people
jump up and get married.
Soon as they’ve passed their last examinations,
looks like they feel themselves fit to get married
and Cicero's words, it would seem that
they consider themselves marriageable.
It’s early morning.
Only this time it’s been raining.
It was absolutely pouring down
with thunderstorms.
Mrs. Gibbs’s garden—
and Mrs. Webb’s here—drenched.
A lot of bean stems and pea pods
are full of water.
All yesterday, over on Main Street
the rain looked like curtains being blown along.
There’s the 5
And there’s Mrs. Gibbs and Mrs. Webb
making breakfast,
I don’t have to point out to the women
in the audience
that both these ladies cooked
three meals a day,
one of ’em for twenty years
and the other for forty—
no summer vacation.
They raised two children apiece,
washed, cleaned the house,
and never had a nervous breakdown.
Never thought themselves hard-used, either —
It’s like what one of those poets said:
‘’You got to love life to have life,
and you got to have life to love life—’’
Do you know who said that?
Thornton Wilder, the author of this play.
As the saying goes – it’s a vicious circle.
Giddy up, Bessie!
Aya, reckon he is.
Now all he’ll be doin’ is pitchin’ hay.
Whoa, Bessie!
Guess I can stop and talk.
I don’t see how he could give
that up  to get married.
Would you, Howie?
Mornin’, Howie!
Good morning
, Bill.
Seein’ if there’s anything
I can do to prevent a flood.
River’s been risin’ all night.
Si Crowell here’s upset George Gibbs
That’s how it goes. In '84 we had a player,
far better than George Gibbs.
His name was Hank Todd.
He went to Maine and become a parson.
Wonderful ballplayer.
Howie, how's the weather?
Not bad. Think maybe
Too bad about the weather. It’s been raining
so heavy that maybe it’ll clear up.
Looks like I’ll need three-a-milk
and two-a-cream.
My wife says to tell you, mrs. Gibbs,
we hope they’ll be happy.
And I’m sure they will.
Thanks, Howie. Tell your wife
I hope she gets to the wedding.
Oh, good morning, Mr. Newsome.
I told you four quarts,
but I hope you can spare another.
Yes
Well— I was just
telling Mrs. Gibbs
My wife
they’ll be happy,
M’s Webb,—know they will.
Thank you,
and thank Mrs. Newsome
Yes, Mrs Webb. We hope to be
there Come on, Bessie!
Well, Ma. You’re losing
one of your chicks.
Yes.
Frank Gibbs,
don’t you say another word.
Sit down and drink your coffee.
The groom’s shaving,
only there ain’t much to shave—
whistling like he's glad
to leave us.—
Every now and then he says “I do” to the mirror,
but it don't sound convincing to me.
Really, Frank,
I don’t know how he’ll get along.
kept his feet and warm things on—
Frank, they’re too young!
He’ll catch his death-a-cold
within a week.
I remember my wedding morning.
I was the searedest young fella
in New Hampshire.
I thought I'd made a mistake.
When I saw you coming down that aisle
I thought you were the prettiest girl
I’d seen;
I was in the Congregational Church
marryin’ a total stranger!
And how do you think I felt?
Frank, w
Farces!
Here, I made you something.
Why, Julia! French toast!
I had to do something.
Yes!
Aya, I get a shock every time I think of George
setting out to be a family man!
There’s nothing so terrifying
in the world as a son.
The relation of father
and son is the damndest, —
Well, mother and daughter’s
no picnic—
They’ll have troubles,
but that’s none of our business.
Everybody has a right
to their own troubles.
Aya… people are meant to live two-by-two in
this world. It’s not good to be all by yourself.
Julia, do you know one of the things I
was scared of when I married you?
I was afraid we didn’t have enough to talk
about for more than  a few weeks.
that we’d eat our meals in silence.
Well, you and I been conversing
for twenty years without
any barren spells.
Well, good weather, bad weather,
I always find something to say.
Did you hear Rebecca up yet?
No. Only day of the year Rebecca hasn’t been
managing everybody’s business.
She’s hiding, might be crying.
Lord’s sakes—
this has got to stop.
Rebecca! Come get breakfast.
Good morning.
Only four more hours to live!
Now, George, put on your boots .
It’s raining torrents.
You don’t go out of this house
without being prepared.
Aw, Ma—it’s just a step.
You’ll catch your
death-a-cold through the service.
George, do what your mother says!
From tomorrow on you can go wherever
and whenever you want,
While you’re in my house
Perhaps Mrs. Webb
isn’t used to callers this early.
Here, take a cup of coffee.
Just a sec.
Good morning, Mother Webb.
Oh my God! You frightened me!
Why not—?
Why, George, the groom can’t see
his bride on his wedding day.
Aw,—that’s  superstition.
Good morning, Mr. Webb.
Good morning, George.
Mr. Webb, you don’t believe
in that, do you?
There’s common-sense
in superstitions, George.
Millions have followed it,
George,
and don’t be the first to fly
in the face of custom.
How is Emily?
She hasn't waked up yet.
Emily’s asleep?
No wonder! We were up all night
sewing and packing.
Now, George; you sit with Mr. Webb
and drink this cup of coffee;
I’ll run upstairs and make sure
Emily doesn’t come downstairs.
There's bacon, too.
But don’t stay long.
Well, George, how are you?
I'm fine. Mr. Webb, what commonsense could
there be in a superstition like that?
Well, on the wedding morning
a girl’s head's full of clothes and—
one thing and another.
That’s probably it?
I never thought of that.
A girl's nervous on her wedding day.
Gee, I wish a person could get married
without all that marching.
It’s the women who’ve built up weddings.
For a while now the women
have it all their own.
A man looks pretty small
at a wedding, George.
All those women making sure the knot’s tied
in a public way.
Well, you believe in it, don’t you,
Mr. Webb?
Yes. Oh, yes! Now,
don’t get me wrong, boy,
marriage is a wonderful thing.
Don’t forget that, George.
No, sir. Mr. Webb, how old were you
when you got married?
Well, I'd been to college and taken
a little time to get settled.
Oh, age hasn’t got much to do with it,
George, compared with—
other things.
What were you going to say, Mr. Webb?
Ah, I don’t know… Was I going to say something?
I was remembering
the other night what my father said
when I got married.
Charles, he said:
start right off showin
Best thing to do is to give an order,
just so she’ll learn to obey,
Then he said: “If anything about her
irritates you,
the tone of her voice, or something else,
get right up and leave the house;
that’ll make it clear to her.”
And he said: "Never let your wife know
how much money you have, never.”
Well…
So I took the opposite
of his advice
and I’ve been happy ever since.
So let that be a lesson to you
never to ask advice
on personal matters
A book came in on the Philo System
of raising chickens.
I wish you’d read it.
I’m thinking of beginning myself,
in the back yard! I’m going to put
an incubator in the cellar—
Charles Webb, are you talking about
that incubator again?
I thought you were talking
about serious things.
Well, Myrtle, if you want to give
the boy some advice,
I’ll go upstairs
George, Emily’s got to eat breakfast!
She sends you her love,
but doesn’t want to see you. Goodbye, George.
Myrtle, guess you didn’t know
about that older superstition.
Since the caveman.
No bridegroom should see
his father-in-law the day of the wedding.
Or a day close to it.
Remember that.
I have to interrupt again.
You see, we want to know how all this began.
The wedding… the plan for two people
to spend their whole lives together.
I'm terribly interested in how
big things like this start.
You know how it is: you’re 21 or 22
and you make some decisions;
then whisssh– you’re 70;
you’ve been a lawyer for 50 years,
and that white-haired lady
by your side
has eaten over fifty thousand meals with you.
How do such things begin?
George and Emily will show you
the conversation they had
when they first knew
”they were meant for one another”.
Before they do I want you to remember
when you were very young,
the days when you were first in love;
when you were like a person
sleep-walking.
You didn’t hear a thing they said to you.
You’re a little bit crazy.
Will you remember that, please?
George has just been elected
that means he will be the senior class
president next year.
And Emily’s just been elected
Secretary and Treasurer.
Goodbye. Oh, Ernestine!
Can you come over tonight
and do Latin ?—
Isn’t Cicero the worst thing?—
Well, tell your mother you have to.
Bye
Emily, can I carry your books home?
Why—uh—thank you. It isn’t far.
’Scuse me, Emily, will you?—
Say, Bob, if I’m a little late,
start practice, and give Herb
some long high ones.
Bye
Hello
I’m glad you were
elected too, Emily.
Thank you.
You’ve been treating me so funny lately.
Well, since you ask,
I might as well say it , George—
Oh, goodbye. Miss Corcoran.
Goodbye, Miss Corcoran.—
What is it?
I don’t like the whole change that’s
come over you in the last year.
Change?
I’m sorry if that hurts your feelings
but I have to tell you the truth.
Wha-what do you mean?
Well, up to a year ago, I used to like you
a lot. I used to watch you —
because we’d been friends so long.
And then you began spending
And you never stopped to speak to anybody
anymore not even to your own family, you didn’t.
George,
ever since you’ve been elected Captain,
and conceited. All the girls say so.
And it hurts to hear 'em say it;
but I agree with ’em
because it's true.
Gosh, Emily. I guess it’s hard
for a fella not to have
some faults creep into his character.
I always expect a man to be perfect.
He has to be like that.
Oh, I—I don’t think it’s possible
to be perfect, Emily.
Well, my father is.
And as far as I can see, your father is.
No excuse why you shouldn’t be, too.
Well, I feel it’s the other way round;
men aren’t naturally good, but girls are.
Well, I’m not perfect.—
It’s not as easy for a girl to be perfect
as a man, because we girls
I don't know what made me say it.
Now I can see it’s not the truth.
Emily—would you like
an ice-cream soda before you go home?
Well, thank you
Hello, Stew, how are you?
Good afternoon, Mrs. Slocum.
Hello, George. Hello Emily.
What’ll you have?—
Why, Emily Webb, what you been
cry in’ about?
She got an awful scare,
Mr. Morgan.
That—that hardware-store wagon
almost ran over her.
Tom Huckins drives like a crazy man.
D
Gets worse every year—
What’ll you have?
No, no, Emily—have an ice-cream with me.
Two strawberry and chocolate
ice-cream, Mr. Morgan.
ice-cream
There are
State Inspector was here yesterday.
And now they’re bringing in
these auto-mo-biles,
best thing to do is just stay home.
Why I can remember when dogs
used to sleep
There you are!
They’re so expensive.
And then do you know what
else I'm celebrating?
I’m celebrating because I've got a friend
who tells me what ought to be told me.
George, don’t think of that.
I don't know
why I said it. It’s not true. You’re—
No,
Emily,
But I’m going to change so quick.
And Emily, I want to ask you a favor.
W-wh-a-t?
I
will you write me a letter once in a while?
I certainly will, George—
It seems like being away
three years
you’d get out of touch with things.
Maybe Grover’s Corners
Grover’s Corners isn’t
a very important place when you think of—
The day wouldn’t come when
I wouldn’t want to know
everything about our town.
I know this is true, Emily.
Well, I’ll try to make
the letters interesting.
Emily, whenever I meet
a farmer I ask him if he thinks
it's important to go to Agriculture School
Yeh, and some of them say it’s
even a waste of time.
You can get all that stuff,
anyway,
in the pamphlets the Government sends out—
Uncle Luke’s gettin’ old,—
he’s about ready for me
to take over his farm.
My!
And like you say,
being gone all that time—
in other places and meeting other people—
I guess new people
probably aren’t any better than old ones.
I feel that you’re as good
a friend as I’ve got.
I don’t need to go and meet new ones.
But George,
maybe it’s important for you
to go and learn all that cattle-judging
and soils and those things.
Of course, I don’t know.
Emily I’m going to make up my mind
right now—I won’t go. Tonight I’ll tell my father.
Why George. I don’t see why you have
to decide right now—
It’s a whole year away.
that fault in my character but there
was one thing wrong.
namely that for a year now I didn't pay
attention to anyone, and...
You, for example. You say you were
watchin’ me when I did everything—
Why, I was doing the same about you.
I always thought about you
as one of the chief people I thought about.
I always made sure where you were  sitting
on the bleachers. And we talked a lot in school
and that was really important to me.
Of course it wasn’t as good as the conversation
we’re having right now.
Then, lately, I started to observe that
you act a bit strange with me.
And for three months not I’ve tried to walk home
with you; but something's always got in the way.
Yesterday, I was waiting for you,
and you walked home with Miss Corcoran.
Oh, George!— Life’s awful funny!
How could I have known that?
I thought—
Listen, Emily, I’m going to tell you why
I’m not going to Agricultural School.
and fond of you, enough to be interested
in your character—
Well, I think that’s just as important
as college is,
even more so.
I think that’s awfully important, too.
Emily, if I make a big change:
could you be—
So I guess—this is an important
talk we've been having—
Yes
Mr. Morgan, I’ll— I’ll have to go home
and get the money.
What’s that? George Gibbs,
do you mean to tell me—
Yes. But I had important motivations,
Mr
Look—here’s my gold watch
to keep until I come back.
That’s all right.
Keep your watch. I’ll trust you.
I’ll be back in five minutes.
I’ll trust you ten years, George —
not a day over.—
Got all over your shock, Emily?
Yes, thank you, Mr. Morgan—
it was nothing.
Well, now we’ll get on to the wedding.
There are a lot of things to be said about a wedding,
and during the wedding there
can be a lot to think about.
We can’t get them all into one
wedding, naturally,—
especially not in Grover’s Corners,
where weddings are mighty short and plain.
In this play I take the part of the minister.
That gives me the right to say
a few things more.
Yes, for a while now the play gets
pretty serious.
Y'see,—some churches say
that marriage is a sacrament.
I don't know what that means exactly,
but I have my suspicions.
A wedding is a god thing. But even
during such a joyful occasion,
many doubts quietly creep
into the heart.
Has the moment truly come
for me to take this important step?
Is this person beside me really
the one and only
whom God and fate have destined for me?
Like one of those European fellas said:
Every time a child is born into the world
it’s Nature’s attempt to make
a perfect human being.
Well, we’ve seen Nature pushing
and contriving for some time now.
We know she’s interested in quantity;
but I think she’s interested in quality, too.
Maybe she's tryin’ to make another
good Governor for New Hampshire.
That’s what Emily hopes.
And don't forget the other witnesses,
Millions of them. Most of them set out
to live two-by-two.
I don’t know why I’m crying.
I guess I have no reason to cry.
as she’s done for 17 years—
And now she’s going to eat in someone
else's house in the morning.
I suppose that’s it— And Emily suddenly said:
‘’
And she put her head on the table
and she cried.
T
out into marriages.
I hope she heard something from
one of her friends.
It’s—it’s cruel, I know;
but I just couldn’t get myself to say anything
The whole world’s wrong,
that’s what’s the matter.
Eh, George!
Look at him, fellas. He’s scared to death!
George! You don’t have to look
so innocent, you old geezer.
We know what you’re thinking.
Go to it, big boy, y’ old geezer you.
All right! That’s enough of that.
There used to be an awful lot
of that kind of thing in weddings in the old days
We’re more civilized now,—so they say.
George! What’s the matter?
Ma, I don’t want to grow old!
Why’s everybody pushing me so?
No, no, George—you’re a man now I
Listen, Ma—for the last time I ask you.
All I want to do is to be a fella—
George! If anyone should hear you!
Why, I’m ashamed of you!
What? Where’s Emily?
George, you gave me such a fright.
Cheer up, Ma. I’m getting married.
Let me catch my breath.
Why, Ma.What are you crying for?
Come on. We got to get ready.
I never felt so alone in my whole life.
And George, over there—I hate him—
I wish I were dead. Papa! Papa!
Sh-h—Emily—Everything’s all right.
Why can’t I stay for a while just as I am?
Let’s go away—
No, no,— Now think a minute.
Don't you remember what you
used to say—that I was your girl.
There must be lots of places
we can go to.
I'd work for you.
I could keep house.
Sh! You musn't think of such things.
You're just nervous, Emily.
George! George! Will you come here a minute!
Why, you're marrying the best
young fellow in the world.
I’m giving away my daughter, George.
Can you take care of her?
I want to—
I love you. I need you.
Well, if you love me, help me—
all I want is someone to love me.
I will, Emily, I'll try.
Come, they're waiting for us.
Now, you know it’ll be all right.
Doesn’t she make a lovely bride?
Do you, George, take this woman,
Emily, to be your wedded wife,
to have and to hold from this day forward,
in sickness and in health,
for richer for poorer,
to love and to cherish till death
do us part?
Loveliest wedding I ever saw.
I really like lovely weddings.
Doesn’t she make a lovely bride?
Yes.
Do you, Emily, take this man, George, to be your
wedded husband?
Don’t know when I’ve seen
such a lovely wedding.
But I always cry. I just like to see
young people happy.
Don’t you? Oh, I think it’s lovely!
…till death do you part?
I do!
The ring!
I’ve married two hundred couples.
Do I believe in it? I don’t know.
I suppose so. X marries Y..
The cottage, the go-cart, the Sunday afternoon
drives with the Ford —
the reading of the will—
Once in a thousand times it’s interesting.
Aren’t they a lovely couple?
I’ve never been on such a lovely wedding.
I'm sure they'll be happy.
I always say: happiness!
This is the most important thing in life!
Gradual changes have taken place
in Grover's Corners.
Horses are gettin’ rarer.
Farmers coming into town now in Fords.
but everybody’s heard about ’em.
This is certainly an important part
often lots of sun and moon and stars.
I often wonder why people like
to be buried in Woodlawn
when they might pass the same time her
Summer people walk around
there laughing
at the funny words on the tombstones.
Iron pennants are on their tombstones.
Had a notion that the Union ought
to be kept together,
though they’d never seen more than
fifty miles of it themselves.
All they knew was the name
This here is the new part of the cemetery.
There’s your friend,
Mrs. Gibbs.
And here's Mr. Stimson,
the
And Mrs. Soames who enjoyed
the weddin' so much, remember?
Oh, and a lot of others.
Wall
while he was on a Boy Scout trip
Yes, an awful lot of sorrow here.
People wild with grief have brought
their relatives up to this hill
rainy days— snow—
You know how it is.
A lot of thoughts come up here,
night and day, but no post office—
We all know that something is eternal
And it ain’t houses or names,
and it ain’t earth, and it ain’t even the stars
and th
All the greatest people ever lived
and yet you’d be surprised how people
are always letting go of that fact.
There’s something way down deep
that’s eternal about every human being.
Y’know, the dead don’t stay interested in us
living people for very long.
Gradually, they let go hold of the earth—
and the people they loved.
Yes, they stay here while the earth-part
of ’em burns away,
and all that time they slowly get
indifferent to what’s goin’ on in Grover’s Corners.
They’re waitin' for something they feel
is cornin’.
Aren’t they waitin’ for the eternal part
in them to come out—clear?
Some of the things they’re going to say
maybe’ll hurt your feelings—
but that’s the way it is: mother 'n daughter
—husband ’n wife—enemy ‘n enemy—
money ‘n miser— all those important things
grow pale around here.
And what's left?
What’s left when memory’s gone?
Well, here are some living people.
Good afternoon, Joe Stoddard
Good afternoon
, good afternoon
I’m Sam Craig.
I should
have
You’ve been away a long time, Sam.
Yes, over twelve years. I’m in business
in Buffalo now, Joe—
But I was in the East when I got news
of my cousin’s death, so I thought
I’d come back and see the old home—
You look well.
Yes, yes, can’t complain—
Very sad, our journey today, Samuel.
Yes.
Yes, yes. I always say, I hate to supervise
I had to come here early today—
my son’s supervisin' at the home
He had lumbago.
Yes, we brought Farmer McCarthy
here a number of years ago now.
Why, this is my Aunt Julia—
I’d forgotten that she’d—of course!
Today’s another bad blow for him.
That’s my sister Carrie’s boy
I’m always uncomfortable when they’re around.
Doesn't sound like Aunt Julia.
I wanted to look
at my father’s and mother’s—
Simon Stimson...
Nobody was supposed to know about it.
He's been through a lot of trouble.
Oh, did he?
Chose his own epitaph.
It ain’t a verse exactly.
Oh, I wouldn’t know. It was wrote up
in the Boston papers at the time.
Had some trouble bringing a baby into
the world. ’Was her second, though.
There's a little boy ’bout four years old.
Yes, there ain’t much more room
over here among the Gibbses,
so they’re opening up a whole
new Gibbs section over by Avenue B.
You’ll excuse me now. I see they’re cornin’.
Well, I declare! The road up here must
have been awfully muddy.
What did she die of?
In childbirth.
Childbirth! I’d forgotten all about that!
My, wasn’t life awful
— and wonderful.
I remember Emily’s lovely wedding.
What a lovely wedding it was!
And her reading the class poem
at Graduation Exercises.
I called on them at their new farm, just before I died.
Perfectly beautiful farm.
It's on the same road we lived on, hm-hm.
Aya, right smart farm.
Good afternoon
It seems thousands and thousands
of years since I—
Mother Gibbs, George and I have
made that farm
into the best place you ever saw.
We thought of you all the time.
We wanted to show you the new barn
and a great long cement drinking fountain
for the stock. We bought that out
of the money you left us.
I did?
Don’t you remember, Mother Gibbs—
the legacy you left us?
Why, it was over three hundred
and fifty dollars
Yes, yes, Emily.
Well, there’s a patent device on this
drinking-fountain so that it never overflows
It won’t be the same to George without me,
but it’s a lovely farm.
Live people don’t understand, do they?
No, dear—not very much.
They’re sort of shut up in little boxes,
aren’t they?
I feel as tho I knew ’em
last a thousand years ago—
My boy is spending the day at Mrs. Carter’s.
Oh, Mr. Carter, my little boy is spending
the day at your house.
Yes, he loves it there.
Mother Gibbs,
we have a Ford, too. Never gives any trouble.
Of being one of them? How long does it
I know
Look, they're finished. They’re going.
Just wait and be patient.
He looks just like George, doesn’t he?
how in the dark live persons are.
Look at him. I loved him so.
From morning till night,
that’s all they are—troubled.
Little cooler than it was.
Aya, that rain’s cooled it off a little.
Those northeast winds always do
the same thing?
If
But Mother Gibbs, one can go back;
one can go back there again into living!
Why just then for a moment
I was thinking about the farm—
and for a minute I was there and my baby
was on my lap as plain as day!
Yes, of course you can.
I can go back there and live
those days over again—why not?
All I can say is, Emily, don’t.
Don’t do it, Emily.
I’ll choose the day I first knew
And as you watch it,
you see the thing that they never know.
You see
t
But is that—painful? Why?
When you’ve been here
longer you’ll see that—
Our life here is to forget all that—
Mother Gibbs,
I’ll choose a happy day, anyway.
It will be important enough.
I can choose a birthday, can’t I?
All right.
It’s February 11th, 1899. A Tuesday.
Do you want any special time of day?
but it stopped the night before, and they
had begun clearing the roads.
Oh, that’s the town I knew as a little girl
And, look, there’s the old white fence
that used to be around our house.
Oh, I’d forgotten that!
I love it so!
They... a
Will she?
And you remember: your father
had been away for a couple of days;
he came back on the early morning train.
No?
Look! There’s Howie Newsome!
Whoa, Bessie!
Morning, Howie.
You’re up early.
Been rescuin’ a party;
darn near froze to death,
down by Polish Town there.
Got drunk and lay out in the snowdrifts.
When I woke him up, he thought he was in bed.
There’s Joe Crowell
Good morning, Joe!
Good mornin’, Mr. Warren.
’Mornin’, Howie.
Children! Wally! Emily!
Time to get up!
You can come dress by the kitchen fire,
if you like, but hurry.
Good mornin’, Mr. Newsome.
Whhh
Minus ten grades, Mis’ Webb.
Think of it! Keep yourself wrapped up.
Come on, Bessie
Mama, I can’t find my blue
hair-ribbon anywhere.
Just open your eyes, dear, that’s all,
I laid it out for you special on the dresser, there.
If it were a snake, it’d bite you.
Good mornin', Bill.
Good mornin’, Mr. Webb.
You’re up early.
Yes, just been back to my old college
in New York
I was called up this mornin’
to rescue a Polish fella—
darn near froze to death.
We must get it in the paper.
How did it go, Charles?
Oh, fine, I guess.
I
Howie Newsome says its ten
below over to his barn.
Yes, well, it's colder than that at Hamilton
College. Students’ ears are falling off.
It ain’t Christian—
Paper have any mistakes?
None that I noticed.
Coffee’s ready
Charles! Don’t forget; it’s Emily’s birthday.
Did you get her anything?
Yes, I’ve got something here.
Where’s my birthday girl?
Hurry up, children! Seven o’clock.
Now I don’t want to call you again.
Why did they ever have to get old?
Mama, I’m here! I'm grown up!
Good morning, Mama.
Well, a very happy birthday
to my girl and many happy returns.
There are surprises waiting
for you on the kitchen table.
Oh,
But birthday or no
I want you to grow up
and be a good strong girl.
That in the blue paper
is from your Aunt Carrie
and I reckon you can guess who brought
the post card album.
George Gibbs— must come over
in the cold — nice of him.
Chew that bacon
It’ll help keep you warm on a cold day.
Mama
,
Mama! His appendix burst
on a camping trip.
We felt terrible,
don’t you remember?
But, just for a moment now we’re all
together— Mama, let’s be happy—
Let’s look at one another!
among your grandmother’s things.
And this is from you! Why, Mama, it’s just
what I wanted. It's beautiful!
He made it at Manual Training class
and he’s very proud of it.
Be sure you make a big fuss.
Your father has a surprise for you, too;
Where
’s my birthday girl?
Happy birthday to you...
I can’t go on!
It goes so fast.
We don’t have time
to look at one another.
I didn’t realize.
So all that was going on
and we never noticed!
Goodbye,
Goodbye, Grover’s Corners
Mama and Papa
and my butternut tree! and Mama’s sunflowers—
and food and coffee—
and bacon that always got burnt onto the pan…
and new-ironed dresses and hot baths—
and sleeping and waking up!
Oh, earth… you’re too wonderful
for anyone to realize you!
every, every minute?
No— Saints and poets maybe—they do some.
Look,
the sky
To move about in a cloud of ignorance;
to go up and down
To spend and waste time as though
you had a million years.
To be always at the mercy of one
self-centered passion, or another.
Ignorance and blindness
That ain’t the whole truth
and you know it, Simon Stimson.
Emily, look at that star.
I forget its name.
My boy Joel was a sailor
—knew
He’d sit on the porch evenin’s and tell
Yes
That’s funny!
It
Mother Gibbs! It’s George!
Sh-h, dear. Just rest yourself.
It
And my Joel, who knew the stars—
he used to say
it took millions of years for that little
speck o’ light to git down to earth.
Goodness!
That ain’t no way to behave.
He ought to be home.
–
Most everybody’s asleep in Grover’s Corners.
There are a few lights on;
their ancient way across the vault of
the sky
Just chalk—or fire.
Only this one is straining away
to make something of itself.
You get a good rest too.
Good night.