Ma rgaret !
Ma rgaret ...
Yes, Doctor ?
– Oh, Ma rgaret , would you make me a cup of coffee? – Yes, of course.
And one for me, please.
And me...
– That's three coffees, then? – Right.
– Hi ! – Hi, Henry.
Hi there...
– Have they been yet? – Not yet.
– Where's Vilma? – Oh, she's slipped out to get some oranges.
Thanks very much.
– Ma rgaret ... – Yes, Doctor?
Sorry about this, but would you mind making another cup of coffee for me?
– Of course not. – Thanks.
– Well? – Well what?
– How goes it? – What, exactly?
– Why, your private studies, of course. – I don't know what you're talking about.
Oh, come off it, Henry — every little child here knows about it !
I don't give a damn what little children know about — I am engaged in no other studies
than those pertaining directly to my work here at the Institute.
I know what it is — you don't trust us, do you?
Can't say I blame you... in certain matters caution is called for.
Especially if one is engaged on two fronts at once...
And what's that supposed to mean?
You're all letting your imaginations run away with you. ..
What about that social tonight - is it still on?
Naturally...
Good morning, sir.
Good morning, friends !
Sit down, sit down, please, you know that neither I nor the Director like to stand on ceremony .. .
So what's the news? Did you all sleep well?
Any problems? I don't see Vilma here.
She phoned to say her bus had broken down.
But she had managed to find a taxi, she said, so she should be here any minute...
Looking forward to the social, are we? I hope you're all coming?
I'm coming, definitely...
We're all coming .. .
Excellent! Personally, I consider our social evenings to be a splendid idea.
Particularly as regards their collectively therapeutic effect.
Simply thanks to the way we, as individuals, invariably loosen up, while, as a collective,
we somehow grow stronger. Wouldn't you say?
Yes, quite, that's exactly how I see it.
Quite apart from the fact that it would be criminal not to make
at least occasional use of such a fine garden !
I came a little earlier on purpose.
Is something wrong?
The Director will tell you himself. All I wanted was to ask you to be sensible —
do try to understand him and don't make unnecessary problems for him,
he is in a difficult enough position as it is. I think we can be glad we have such a Director,
we're really doing ourselves a favour. It is therefore up to us to display
at least a minimum of self-discipline so that neither he, our Institute,
nor any one of us should get into hot water.
I'm sure you understand and won't expect me to say more than I've already said and am able to say.
We're all adults, after all, are - we not?
Yes, of course.
There you are, then ! Have you had your soap ration?
– They're due to bring it today. – Excellent!
Good morning, Director.
Hello there, friends. Do sit down, please, you know that I don't like to stand on ceremony.
That's just what I told our colleagues just now, Director !
– Did you sleep well? – Yes, thank you.
– Do you have any problems? – No, I don't think so .
Where is Vilma?
She phoned to say her bus had broken down. But she had managed to find a taxi,
she said, so she should be here any minute.
– Here it is. – Thanks.
Don't mention it.
Looking forward to the social, are we?
Very much, Director.
I have good news for you, friends. The Director has promised to make a short appearance at our social.
A short one?
That'll depend on the circumstances. I hope you'll show up?
Yes, of course, Director.
Look here, colleagues, no sense in making a meal of it.
We all have work to do. So let me get straight to the point: as you probably know,
there have lately cropped up complaints that our Institute isn't fulfilling its tasks
in keeping with the present situation...
What situation?
But my dear colleague, Neuwirth, let's not beat about the bush.
Are we not the people who're supposed to be the first to know things,
and the first to take action? That’s why they’re paying us.
But to continue: w e're being urged, with increasing insistence, that we go over to the offensive.
Firmly in the spirit of the scientific…
That, surely, goes without saying?
I'm sorry, Director, but unfortunately there exists science that is not based on a scientific view of the world...
That is no science where I'm concerned! Now, where was I?
You were saying that we must somehow try and implement...
In order to counter the isolated but nevertheless alarming expressions
of various irrational viewpoints which can be discerned in particular in certain members
of our younger generation and which owe their origin to the incorrect...
Now, where was I?
You were saying that the irrational…
…interpretation of the complexity of natural processes and the historical dynamism
of human civilisation, some of whose aspects are taken out of context,
only to be interpreted, either in the light of pseudoscientific theories...
We have discovered that copies of some of the works of C.J. Jung are circulating among our young people...
... Or in the light of a whole range of mystic prejudices, superstitions, obscure teachings
and practices spread by certain charlatans, psychopaths and members of the intelligentsia...
Sorry to be late, Director, but just imagine — the bus I was on...
– Yes, I've heard. Sit down. – Thank you.
Look here, colleagues, no sense in making a meal of it. We all have work to do.
I have already acquainted you with the size of the problem and the tasks it puts in front of us.
Now it is up to you. All I want to do is to ask you to be sensible,
try and understand and don't make unnecessary problems for me in what is a difficult enough position as it is.
It’s  good cause, after all! We live in modern times, after all.
W e do.
There you are, then ! Have you had your soap ration?
They're due to bring it today .. .
I rely on you, Henry...
– You mean, where the soap is concerned? – The soap and everything else.
– Who is it? – It's only me, Doctor.
Just a moment !
Come in, Mrs Houbova.
Oh dear, the place is full of smoke! You need a bit of air.
Yes, right, in a minute. .. a nything wrong?
You have a visitor.
– Have I? Who is it? – I don't know, he didn't tell me.
A stranger, is it?
He’s never been here. Never seen him before.
What does he look like?
I dunno — how should I say, a bit disreputable... and, worst of all, he…
– He…? – I hardly like to say...
– Go on, out with it, Mrs Houbova! – Well, it's just that he… smells...
Is that so? How does he smell?
Hard to say — like a strong cheese, I guess.
Never mind, tell him to come in .. .
You're to go in…
– Good afternoon. – How do you do, Mr. Foustka.
Very cosy, very cosy indeed. Just as I imagined it.
All these learned books... a rare globe... everything nice and restrained... balance in all its glory. ..
What balance? And anyway, who am I speaking to?
All in good time. May I sit down?
Please do…
I take it I don't have to stress that you should not mention my visit
to anyone in your own interest as well as mine?
Why should I not mention it?
You'll see soon enough.
My name is Fistula.
My place of work is immaterial — in any case I don't have a permanent job.
Don't have to, you see, being retired as an invalid.
I'd hazard a guess that you work in a match factory.
Athlete's foot, my dear sir, or some similar ailment I suffer from, and there's little I can do about it.
Aren't you going to ask me what it is I want? What is the purpose of my visit?
Well, I have not yet given up the hope that you will tell me without being asked.
Of course, there is nothing to prevent me doing just that, and if I haven't done so already, then for a very good reason.
What reason is that?
I had rather hoped you'd discover that for yourself.
How can I know when I see you for the first time?
And anyway, I have neither the time nor the inclination to play silly guessing games.
Unlike you, I happen to have a job and will shortly have to go…
I know, to your Institute's social. You have bags of time.
How did you know I'm going to our social?
And before I arrived you didn't exactly carry on like a man in a hurry.
You can't know anything about what I was doing before you arrived.
Forgive me, but I know far more than you about, what I know
and what I don't know, and how I know what I know.
– Look here, Mr... – Fistula...
I'm asking you straight, and I expect a straight answer: what is it you want?
Does the name Marbuel mean anything to you? Or Loradiel? Or Lafiel?
Out!
– I beg your pardon? – I said: o ut!
How do you mean out?
Leave my flat at once and never show your face here again !
Did you hear what I said?
I heard what you said...
... and I'm delighted at your reaction
because it confirms that I have come to the right address...
I don't understand...
Your agitation tells me that you're well aware of the weight of my contacts,
which you would hardly be in a position to know unless you had earlier taken
an interest in them yourself .. .
Those names mean nothing to me, I have no idea what you're talking about,
and the suddenness of my decision to throw you out is due simply to the fact that
I have suddenly had enough of you.
Leave my flat at once and never show your face here again!
Your first request — that I leave — I'll naturally comply with, even though not just yet;
the second I will not, and you will in time be very grateful to me for it.
I'm afraid you didn't understand. Those weren't two mutually independent requests
— in fact, they weren't requests at all. It was a command, single and indivisible.
Understood. However, I must add: the alacrity with which you subsequently
attributed a different motive to that command, all this proves just one thing:
that your original fear of me as a representative of those contacts has given way to a fear of me
as a possible agent provocateur. I therefore have to tell you that this, too, I anticipated.
Nay, what is more, if this had not happened I should have found it suspicious
and would have had to ask myself if indeed you are not an agent provocateur.
But now let's get down to the matter in hand. There is of course no way I can prove to you
that I am no provocateur; even were I to call forth Ariel himself, here and now,
it would not exclude the possibility that I am also trying to provoke you.
You thus have only three choices: you can continue to consider me
an agent provocateur and insist that I leave.
Secondly: not to think of me in those terms but instead to trust me.
Thirdly: not to make your mind up in this matter just yet and to adopt a waiting posture,
which means not to throw me out but on the other hand to say nothing which,
if I were an agent provocateur, I might be able to use against you.
If I may, I'd recommend the third alternative...
All right. I should add, though, that in talking to you, I have no need to watch
what I say because there is no question that I might think, much less utter,
anything that could be used against me.
Splendid! I like you. If I were an agent provocateur, I'd have to admit
that you have passed your first test with flying colours !
Your words betray a wellfounded caution as well as your sharp intelligence and ready wit,
all of which are qualities I can but welcome, for they give me hope that I can rely
on you and that we shall work well together.
– Now, listen here, Mr... – Fistula...
Listen here, Mr Fistula, I'd just like to say two things.
Firstly: To my mind you talk too much and I wish you'd come more quickly
to the point and tell me what brought you here.
You have given me no indication, even though I asked you for a straight answer to my straight question.
And secondly: I’m surprised to hear that you and I are supposed to be working together.
It takes two to play, you know.
You have just used eighty words to reply to me.
Considering their semantic value, that is not exactly a small number,
so I would not accuse others of talking too much if I were you.
Loquaciousness is well known to be infectious...
I hope that in time you will also acquire some of my more important skills.
Are you trying to tell me you want to teach me things?
– Not just teach... – No? What else, for God's sake?
Leave him out of this!
What else do you have in mind, then?
To initiate you...
That's enough! I am a scientist and hold a scientific world view,
working in a very responsible position in one of our foremost scientific institutes !
If anyone comes to me with ideas that can be defined
as an attempt to spread superstition, I shall be forced to act according to my scientific conscience.
Doctor, I am well acquainted with your views, I know how much your work at the Institute
means to you, so please accept my apologies for my stupid joke.
In any case, it's high time I abandoned these introductory pleasantries.
As your Director was good enough to stress this morning, one of the tasks facing your Institute
is to combat certain expressions of irrational mysticism.
As a scientist, you yourself know best that this struggle of yours will be the more effective,
the more thorough your knowledge of that which you are struggling against.
You have in your possession a remarkable collection of hermetic literature,
but as you well know, theory is not everything, and I'd seriously doubt that you have never felt
the urge to acquaint yourself directly with contemporary magical practice.
I come to you as a practitioner with several hundred successful magical evocations behind him,
who is prepared to acquaint you with some aspects of his work in order to provide
valuable material for your scientific studies.
And if you are asking yourself how it is possible for a hermetic to take an interest
in the struggle against hermetism, I can give you a frank answer:
I find myself in a situation where, without some support, I might come to a sticky end.
I therefore offer myself to you as a subject for study, and I shall ask for nothing more
in return than that you should, if necessary, testify that I have put myself at the disposal
of science and that it would thus be unfair to hold me responsible for spreading
something that I am, in actual fact, helping to combat.
– I have a suggestion... – Yes? I'm listening...
In order to expedite matters, I'll pretend not to be equipped with a scientific world view,
as if I were taking an interest in certain things out of mere curiosity.
Agreed!
Ouch!
Man, your temperature must be fifty below!
Not that much…
Well? What is it? Lost your tongue all of a sudden?
– I'm waiting... – Waiting for what?
– Your wishes. – I don't understand — what wishes?
How can I acquaint you with my knowledge unless you set me certain tasks
such as you can yourself verify? Or those that are important to you for some reason?
Oh, I see. What kind of tasks do you have in mind — roughly?
Come, you know enough about these things !
Yes, perhaps, but faced with this opportunity of a practical demonstration…
No matter, I'll help you. How about this for an innocent first step.
As far as I know, you fancy a certain young lady...
I don't know what you're talking about...
Oh come, Doctor, after all that has been said here,
surely you cannot doubt that I might be privy to a secret or two...
If you mean the secretary at the Institute, I don't deny that she is pretty, but that hardly entitles you...
What if tonight at that social of yours she were to fall in love with you?
– Please go away! – Who? Me? Why?
Yes, you. Go away.
You're not starting that again? Just when I thought we had come to an understanding.
– You have insulted me. – Insulted you? How?
I'm not so desperate that I need to turn to magic in matters of love!
Do you think I'm so badly off that I am neither a weakling, incapable of going without
that which I can't achieve by my own efforts, nor yet a scoundrel who would conduct
experiments on an unsuspecting innocent girl !
None of us really knows what we're capable of ! But that's not the point.
If my well-meant, innocent, spur of-the-moment little idea offends you in any way,
I naturally apologise and withdraw it.
And another thing: I have a girl friend and I am faithful to her.
– As she is to you? – What are you saying?
Forget it…
No, just a minute — you can't get away with hints and double entendres !
I'm not interested in gossi p , and I don't like loose tongues !
Sorry I spoke. If you have decided to turn a blind eye, that is entirely your business...
Are you leaving? I just let off a little steam.
– So what's to become of it? – What's to become of what?
– Our agreement, I mean. – Well?
– Is it still on? – That is entirely up to you.
We have to realise that out of the infinite number of possible velocities,
the expansion of the universe chose precisely the one which gave rise to the universe
as we know it, that is, with sufficient time and other prerequisites for the formation
of solid bodies, so that life could exist on them —
or at least on one of them! Isn't that a remarkable coincidence?
Yes, quite remarkable !
Yes, isn't it ? And if you delve further, you'll discover that you owe your existence
to such an incredible number of equally incredible coincidences that it exceeds
all conceivable ratios of probability.
All this cannot surely be an accident, behind it must be concealed some more profound intention
of existence, of the world and of nature.
Does it not strike you as if the cosmos had actually determined to see itself one day
through our eyes and to put the questions which we are now putting, with our lips?
Oh yes, that's exactly how it strikes me !
Having a good time, you two?
– We have been discussing some philosophical questions... – In that case, don't let me disturb you...
And another thing: modern biology has long been aware that while the law
of the survival of the fittest and similar discoveries explain a great deal,
they fail altogether to explain why life should exist in the first place in the endless variety
of its frequently quite self-serving manifestations, which would seem to be here
only because existence wishes to display its own power.
For whose sake, though? Have you given any thought to this?
Not quite in this way, I must confess. ..
...b ut now, I guess I'll think about it always; you know how to put it so nicely.
– May I have the pleasure? – Yes... of course.
– You'll come back, won't you? – But of course! It's all so terribly interesting...
A splendid evening, isn't it?
Why, yes... we've been lucky with the weather...
– Do sit down. May I join you? – Yes, please do…
– Henry... – Yes?
Tell me frankly — what do you think of me?
What do I think?
Well, how should I say, I think that everyone at the Institute is glad that you are in charge...
No, you don't understand. What I want to know is what you personally think of me — as a man...
or, to put it more accurately: what are your feelings towards me?
– I feel great respect for you... – Is that all?
Well... how to say it… it's very difficult...
So here you are, Director. We've been looking for you...
Anything wrong?
Nothing in particular. It's only that Petruska here wants to ask you something but is too shy to say so…
Ask me what?
She wants to ask you whether you would dance with her…
I'm afraid I don't know how to lead, I'd only trample her dress.
But there are so many better dancers here...
In that case, would you at least accept our invitation and accompany us to the pond,
where colleague Kotrly has built a delightful underwater light display.
Have you seen my underwater light display yet?
– You're doing it all wrong, Vilda. – What am I doing wrong?
You're crawling so abjectly that before long those two idiots
will get fed up with you and you'll be the laughing-stock of the Institute.
Apart from which, everyone will want to see you come a cropper.
Maybe I am doing it all wrong, but that's still better than pretending
I'm not interested and at the same time telling 'em everything...
I take it you're referring to Neuwirth?
Who else? Who was it first started blabbing about Foustka's dabbling in magic?
If they get to hear of it, it'll be Neuwirth's doing!
But we all talked about it! You're being unfair to Neuwirth,
your only excuse being that it is out of jealousy...
I might have known you'd take his side!
P lease don't start that again!
Liba, give me your word there is nothing between you !
– I give you my word ! How about another dance? – Okay!
Oh, well, let me not disturb you...
Go on, talk some more! Each word of yours seems to open my eyes...
I can't understand how I could have been so blind — so superficial...
I'll start, if you'll allow me, from a completely different angle.
Have you ever thought that we would be quite unable to understand even
the most simple moral action which is not motivated by self-interest,
that in fact it would appear to be quite absurd, if we did not admit to ourselves
that somewhere within it there is concealed the prerequisite of something higher,
some absolute, omniscient and infinitely just moral authority, through which
and in which all our actions gain a mysterious worth and through which each
and every one of us constantly touches eternity?
Yes, yes, that's exactly how I've always felt it to be !
Only I was never able to say it, much less put it into such splendid words !
There you are! All the more tragic, then, that modern man has chosen to deny
everything that is larger than him, to deride the very notion that there might be something
higher and that could possibly have some higher meaning !
Having set himself up as the highest authority, he then watches in horror where the world is heading.
Isn't it all so clear and simple! So different from the way people usually talk about them...
and you take it all so seriously ! I don't think I'll ever forget this evening.
I feel as if, in your company, I was becoming a new person every minute —
please don't be annoyed that I'm being so frank, but you seem to emanate a...
I don't understand how I could have been indifferent to you all this time...
I've never felt anything like this before.
May I have the pleasure?
Oh, I'm sorry, but...
Oh, come on Ma rgaret — we haven't danced together yet.
– You'll wait here for me, won't you? – Yes, of course.
Alone again, are you?
Can you smell that? Acacia... evening primrose...
I'm not much of a fragrance expert.
– Henry. . . – Yes?
– Would you like to be my deputy? – Me?
I could swing it…
– But you already have a deputy. – I’m fed up with him!
– Henry... – Yes?
How about coming back to my place when this is over?
Or we needn't stay till the end, simply disappear.
I have some home-made cherry brandy and I'd show you my collection of miniatures,
and we could have a good chat, undisturbed.
If it got late, and you didn't feel like making your way home,
you could stay the night. What do you say?
Thank you very much, I appreciate your invitation, but you see, I've already promised...
Vilma?
So here you are, Director ! We've been looking for you...
Anything wrong?
Nothing in particular. We just wanted to ask you what you're doing after this is over.
We should be honoured if you'd accept our invitation for a nightcap.
Of course, you can sleep at our place, should you wish...
No, I'm sorry, I am very tired. I have to go home...
I've seen a lot, but the sight of an educated man trying to curry favour
with his cretinous bosses with tricks such as those coloured bulbs in the pond — that really takes the biscuit!
I'd say it's better to curry favour with those coloured bulbs in the porid than to pretend a lack of interest
and at the same time tell 'em everything !
I might have known you'd take his side!
D on't start that again!
Liba, give me your word there is nothing between you !
– I give you my word. How about another dance? – Sure.
D on't let me disturb you.
When man drives God out of his heart, he makes way for the Devil.
It is well known that the Devil is a master of disguise.
Can one imagine a more ingenious disguise than that offered him by our modern lack of faith?
Doubtless he finds he can work best where people have stopped believing in him.
That is why destruction in today's world can best be carried out under the banner
of science, and in this way we scientists have become the grotesque standard-bearers of this destruction...
Forgive me for speaking so frankly, Ma rgaret , but I cannot hold it back any longer !
And who else should I confide in but you?
I love you!
No!
Yes, and I'll go on loving you till the day I die !
You unhappy girl! With me you'd be doomed !
Rather doomed with you and in truth, than to live without you and live a lie.
Having a good time?
– When was he here last? – Who?
Oh, don't ask such stupid questions!
You mean that dancer?
About a week ago...
And you let him in?
He just brought me a bunch of violets.
I told him I didn't have time, that I was meeting you...
I asked whether you let him in. ..
I don't remember... maybe he did come in for a while...
So you kissed each other !
I kissed him on the cheek when he gave me those violets. That's all.
Vilma, be so kind as not to treat me like an idiot. A kiss on the cheek!
Once you let him in I'm sure he’d at least want to dance with you.
Henry, please leave ft alone !
Can't you find something more interesting to talk about?
Did he or didn't he?
All right, if you must know, he did. And that's all I'm going to say.
I refuse to discuss this any longer. As if you didn't know that I love you
and that no dancer can pose a threat to you.
So please no more of this interrogation !
After all, I don't give you the third degree — even though I have more reason to than you !
So you refuse to answer? That, of course, speaks for itself.
I have told you again and again that he means nothing to me, I don't go out of my way to see him,
I don't dance with him. What more am I supposed to do, damn it?
He's always flitting around you, flattering you, wanting to dance with you ,
and you lap it up! If you didn't, you'd have put an end to it long ago.
I don't deny his attentions flatter me !
I'm touched by his persistence, the way he refuses to give up even though he knows he hasn't got a chance.
Would you be capable of turning up here at night, from devil knows where,
just to hand me a bunch of violets — at the same time knowing it was hopeless?
He persists because you deny him in a way that kindles his hope,
and you resist him in a fashion that fuels his desire. You whore!
You have obviously made up your mind to insult me.
For how long did you dance with him?
Now that's really enough, Henry , y ou're becoming a bore !
I've known for a long time that you're something of an eccentric,
but I'd never have guessed you could be so nasty !
You seem to be in the grip of a pathological jealousy.
And you're being insensitive, tactless, petty minded and vengeful to boot!
If at least, you had a real reason...
So you intend to go on whoring?
You have no right to speak to me like this! You spent the whole evening dancing
attendance on that girl, embarrassing everybody in sight,
while I trotted around like an idiot — and we end up with you making
a scene on account of some dumb dancer. How ridiculous can you get!
Do you realise how unjust it all is? Do you understand how selfish and cruel you've become?
First of all: I don't dance attendance on anybody, and I won't have you speak
about such a pure being as Margaret.
And secondly: we're not now talking about me but about you,
so kindly don't try to change the subject!
Sometimes it seems to me that there is some monstrous plan behind all this:
you first of all arouse feelings in me which I had thought long dead,
and then you weave your treacherous web around my heart
But I'm not going to let myself be stretched on this rack any longer !
I'm going to do something to myself... or him... or you— or all of us!
– Your performance gets better every day… – Well, you're pretty good yourself.
– Henry… – Yes?
– Don't you get tired of it at times? – Tired of what?
– Of me making you take part in these games? – It did irritate me at first.
– And now? – Now it's beginning to scare me...
Scare you? Why is that?
It seems to me I'm beginning to take it too seriously .. .
Henry! You're not really getting jealous, are you?
T hat's too crazy!
Not in my wildest dreams would I have thought such a success possible !
I had become reconciled to you showing only feigned jealousy...
Sorry, but I can't share your enthusiasm.
I don't see what it is you're afraid of ...
Of myself !
Go on!
No, don't underestimate it, Vilma. Something is going on inside me —
I feel I'd be capable of doing things that were always alien to me.
As if something that had lain hidden deep inside me was suddenly floating to the surface.
For once you feel a little healthy jealousy !
There's nothing the matter with you, maybe you're a little disconcerted
by the goings on at the Institute, especially after last night's unfortunate encounter with the Directo r.
If only it were as simple as that...
You think he'll destroy you?
He'll certainly try. Question is, does he have the necessary power?
He has as much power as he wants — certainly where we're concerned .. .
But there are other kinds of power than that which he happens to wield.
– You're serious, aren't you? – Yes.
Now you are scaring me !
P romise me you won't dabble in anything of that sort !
What if I don't promise?
I told you that invalid would bring us nothing but misfortune !
He's got you all muddled !
Don't tell me you would really take him up on his suggestion?
– Well, why not? – That's dreadful!
At least you can see I wasn't just letting off steam.
– Good evening. Is Vilma in? – Why?
I just wanted to give her something...
Vilma, you've got a visitor...
I s that you?
Sorry to bother you so late... We had a performance in the countryside...
and... I just wanted to give you this...
Thank you...
Well, I'll be off again... sorry if I disturbed you...
– Bye. – Bye .
I love you .. .
Don't tell me we're the first!
Have you noticed that you only arrive on time when I sleep at your place?
You do exaggerate...
Margaret...
Would you make us a coffee? Strong ones, if possible.
Yes … of course...
Did you sleep well?
Yes, thank you, well... why no, not really... I had so much to think about...
You really managed to turn the poor girl's head last night.
Oh, she'll get over it.
– Henry... – Yes, darling?
I can't remember when we made love so beautifully...
– Oh, you're here already. – Surprised, aren't you?
– What on earth is that? – Unbridled passion .
Thank you. ..
– How about us? – Yes, of course, Doctor...
Good morning, Deputy .
Good morning, friends !
I see that today you're all here early , s plendid !
T hough today of all days I'd hardly have expected it. ..
Well, I believe we had a most successful evening last night.
You all deserve thanks for that. Of course, special recognition goes
to Kotrly here for his underwater lighting effects. ..
Oh, that was nothing…
No point, friends, in beating about the bush...
Anything wrong?
The Director will tell you himself. All I wanted was to ask you to see things
as they are, and to try and help us as we try to help you.
There are moments in life when people either show their mettle —
in which case they have nothing to fear — or they don't measure up.
But you're all educated people, and so I don't have to draw you a picture, do I?
Now, who'll volunteer to clear up the garden?
I will, if you like. I have to remove all those bulbs anyway. ..
Splendid !
Good morning, Director. ..
Good morning, friends. I see that today you're all here early , splendid!
T hough today of all days I'd hardly have expected it !
That's just what I told our colleagues just now, Director.
A nd yet it is particularly important this morning...
– Did you sleep well? – Yes, thank you.
– Do you have any problems? – No, I don't think so…
Look here, colleagues, no sense in making a meal of it…
Anything wrong?
As we all know, our Institute is a kind of lighthouse of true knowledge,
indeed I might say it is — in its role of a vigilant guardian of the very scientific nature of science —
something like the avant-garde of progress.
Yes, Director, I have already reminded our colleagues of the responsibility this role places on all of us…
But why am I telling you all this : s omething serious has happened.
Anything wrong?
Please don't interrupt the Director. He's just about to tell us…
Something serious has happened. The virus has lodged where one would least
have expected it but where, at the same time, it can cause the most damage —
that is, in the very centre of the antivirus campaign or, to stay with the metaphor —
in the central store of antibiotics.
Are you telling us, Director, that right here ... s omeone ... that one of us...
Yes, that's exactly what I am telling you, filled as I am with deep sorrow, shame and indignation.
We have here in our midst, in this scientific institute ,
I underline the word scientific — someone who for a long time now and
of course in complete secrecy, which only goes to show his two-faced character,
has been engaged in various so-called hermetic practices, seeking in these murky waters
the hidden treasure of allegedly higher — in other words, pre-scientific learning.
Any questions?
May we know the name of this colleague?
Tell them !
I can scarcely bring myself to say it, but name him I must.
Very well then — it is Dr Foustka.
A nyone else wish to speak?
Yes, I do….
No , please stay out of this!
This concerns us all without exception , so let our miss secretary share her opinion as well..
Forgive me, Director, I am no scientist and I don't know how to put it —
but this simply can't be true! Dr Foustka is a wise and honourable man.
H e worries about things which by rights we all should be worrying about —
he tries to think things out for himself... to get to the bottom of things...
the sources of morality ... the order of the universe...
All the rest — all this talk about those contacts... I simply don't believe it.
I'm sure it's all just gossip, put about by malicious people who wish to harm him.
When we finish here, please arrange for her immediate dismissal.
Yes, Director!
Our Institute really cannot now afford the luxury of employing secretaries
who accuse the management of lying !
You can go and pack your things...
What possessed you? So needlessly to ruin your life — who'll give you a job after this?
I want to suffer with you!
Excuse me, Director, would it not be more sensible to send her for treatment?
You can see she doesn't know what she is saying.
Psychiatric hospitals are not a cloakroom where one deposits girls whom one first
confuses with highfalutin ideas and then wants to get rid of.
Are you renouncing me, Henry? And renouncing everything you told me last night?
Be quiet, do you hear?
If she does something foolish, it'll be your fault !
You'd like that, wouldn't you?
– Don't start... – Who's starting? Me?
Quiet ! I'll enquire upstairs whether she might not be able to take a job as a cleaner with one of the housing administrations.
That would be a sensible and humane solution...
Do you wish to make use of your right to respond to the accusation that has been made against you?
Director, Deputy Director, colleagues. I am confident that my case will be dealt
with fairly and objectively, and I suppose therefore that when the time comes
I shall be given the opportunity to give a more detailed explanation.
For the time being, however, I shall confine myself to expressing the hope that
the investigation will be unprejudiced
and have the one and only aim of uncovering the truth.
We are living in modern times and no one here has the slightest intention of staging a witch hunt.
That would only be to revive the old ignorance and fanaticism, against which we are fighting.
Truth must prevail, whoever suffers in the process !
Who has volunteered to tidy up the garden?
I did, Director .. .
I am delighted that you have taken on this task, Vil da .
I shall come and give you a hand. ..
– What are you doing here? – Waiting for you.
How did you get in?
No, not through the chimney, if that's what you fear. I came in through the door,
which Mrs Houbova kindly opened for me before she went off to do her shopping.
You see, I explained to her that you urgently wanted to speak to me and that,
given my gammy leg, I could hardly be expected to wait outside.
You mean you lied to her , as usual.
Don't you believe that I'm an invalid?
That I do. You lied when you pretended that I was anxious to see you.
The truth is, on the contrary, that after everything that's happened, I was hoping to never see you again.
On the contrary: what has happened makes our meetings that much more desirable !
How dare you rummage among my papers?
Well, I had to find something to do while I waited...
And what about those shoes?
D on't be such an old fusspot...
P retty successful so far, wouldn't you agree?
Successful? What might you be referring to?
I'd never have expected you to manage it so quickly and so easily.
You're a good learner, I must say.
I have no idea what you're talking about...
Oh yes, you have. Did we not agree first of all to carry out a little innocent experiment?
And it succeeded beyond all expectation, don't you think?
If you mean that that wretched child developed a crush on me, let me just tell you two things .
F irst : that was no work of magic, much less your doing.
All that happened was that I had...
Quite by chance...
…an opportunity to talk to her properly for the first time, and that, as it happens...
By chance...
…I was on form that night, so that she found what I had to say interesting.
Well, and as such girls do, her interest soon switched...
By chance...
…from the topic of conversation to the speaker.
I can't see anything there that would in any way be out of the ordinary.
And, secondly: seeing what consequences this event had for the girl, I bitterly regret that
it ever happened, even though I had no idea — how could I?
that our innocent talk would have such consequences...
W hat's so funny?
My dear Doctor! We all know that you don't believe in such unscientific things
as mere chance and the workings of coincidence.
You have obviously not asked yourself how it was that you,
who up till then were just about capable of requesting her to make you a cup of coffee,
were suddenly waxing so eloquently in front of the girl,
courageously spouting ideas which you well knew could put your career at the Institute in jeopardy.
Does it not seem odd to you that this should have happened just when we had hatched our little scheme?
And does it not surprise you that your ideas alone —
as if someone had waved a magic wand — overcame all the girl's inhibitions,
kindling a love that nothing can destroy?
W e all have our moments when we somehow manage to transcend ourselves...
That is what I'm talking about!
I don't understand...
You surely didn't think that the spirit of love Je l iel would turn up
in person at your social and arrange everything for you like some mundane matchmaker?
How else do you think he could fix it except through you yourself?
It's quite simple, really : he, so to speak, took over your body.
Or rather: he aroused and liberated something in you that's always been there but had lain dormant until then.
You don't say!
The human mind, after all, is not an inert mass —
you must know that better than I do, being a scientist.
If the seed is to sprout, someone has first to sow it…
If — I say if— you and your... whatever-his-name-is...
Your Je l iel are in any way responsible for this unfortunate seeding,
then I curse the two of you from the bottom of my heart.
You're a devil and I don't want to have anything more to do with you.
Why are you being so dense? If the devil exists, then he is within u s!
In that case you must be his favourite abode.
You overestimate me. Can you not understand a simple fact: I am no more than a catalyst,
helping my fellow-men to bring out something that exists in them without my intervention !
We only live once, so why should we spend those few decades that are allotted to us
stifling under the gag of life-denying scruples?
You know why you called me a devil?
To rid yourself of responsibility and to ease your conscience by.
I do hope that you will succeed in outwitting your scruples in this way.
But you must understand that I — an insignificant invalid called Fistula —
could not budge you by so much as an inch if you did not want to be budged,
if indeed you had not dreamed about it long ago.
Our little experiment was merely designed to bring these trivialities home to you .. .
In that case what was all that about its being so innocent?
Nothing but a barefaced lie!
Wrong again! You are once more only trying to lie to yourself !
You could easily have told the girl how infallible was the scientific view of the world,
you could have expounded on the worldshattering importance of the work
your Institute is doing, and she would have been quite safe !
But that's not the point. I really have to compliment you on one thing —
that, for a beginner, you acquitted yourself really well.
Your disguise in the saintly habit of an impassioned seeker after as the true source
of the meaning of the universe and of all moral imperatives —
that was truly magnificent! You chose the very method that is also Je l iel's classic method.
I take my hat off to you !
What disguise? I was only giving expression to my thoughts !
– My dear friend... – I am no friend of yours!
My dear sir, truth is not merely what we are thinking, but also why,
to whom and under what circumstances we say it.
I don't know how they managed it, but somehow they've found out that
I have had contact with you, and as a result it is highly likely that I'll be fired,
made an example of, publicly disgraced, and no doubt existentially and many other ways completely destroyed.
It will be a just punishment for my unforgivable irresponsibility, for my having succumbed
to temptation, under the influence of a poisonous, unsubstantiated, evil jealousy
which my overweening pride caused to grow within me.
Thus I tried to kill two birds with one stone, to gain the affections of one and to hurt another.
Yes, I was blinded by some devilish impulse in my heart, and I must therefore
be grateful to you for helping me realise this.
Your explanation has served to throw light on the true source of my error,
which as you rightly say has yet again to be sought inside me and nowhere else.
I therefore do not regret our meeting — if that's the word for the way you insinuated yourself into my life.
I have learned an important lesson, and your dark intentions have helped to illuminate my own behaviour.
I am telling you all this because — I firmly hope and believe —
this is the last time I shall see you. Arid that you will leave this very minute.
I am as well acquainted with the thought processes you have just been kind enough
to demonstrate for me as I am with these old shoes of mine.
Whenever a beginner successfully breaks the carapace of his or her earlier inhibitions,
thus giving free passage to all one's latent possibilities,
there follows the inevitable hangover, accompanied by a bout of what I can only call
masochistic self-accusation and self-chastisement.
In short, he turns it into a sort of little dance-floor on which to perform the ritual celebration of his principles.
All right ! I have had just about as much as I can stand! If you think for a minute
that by your speechifying you're again going to inveigle me into
some dubious adventure, you're bloody well mistaken!
No, my dear sir, it is you who are mistaken if you fondly believe that you're not inveigled already...
Get out!
May I just point out that when you return to reality and, who knows,
feel like consulting me, I may not be there to be consulted.
Just go away , please!
Driven by her unreasoning jealousy because he had the audacity
to spend a few minutes in a philosophical discussion with another woman,
his mistress shops him to his superiors and tells them
he has had contacts with a magician...
What's that? You're a damn liar!
That just goes to show how little you know women.
I just do not believe Vilma would lend herself to something as vile as this.
After all the sunny moments of pure happiness we've known together!
What do you say, what should I do?
Forget it. ..
Well, what would you suggest I do?
You should have realised by now that I don't go around dispensing advice
or fixing things. At most I'll occasionally provide someone with a stimulus...
Don't talk in riddles, damn you!
All you have to do is to summon up, in a good cause, at least a small fraction
of the cunning which your dear Director makes use of, in pursuance
of wicked causes, from morning till night !
Who's now going to make us coffee? – Why don't you go and make it?
Why don't you?
– Hello… – Hi…
– Have they been yet? – Not yet. ..
– Poor M argaret ... – What about her?
– Why, she tried to cut her wrists... – So it is true...
– They say she's in the psycho ward... – The poor thing...
Good morning, sir deputy .
Good morning, friends !
Sit down, please...
– I don't see Vilma here. – She's had to go to the dentist.
As you all know, we have a difficult task before us today.
No one here — as the Director so aptly put it —
has any intention of carrying out a witchhunt.
Truth must prevail, whoever suffers in the process.
But all the more reason for us to remember that to seek the truth means to seek
the whole and unembellished truth.
The truth, my friends, is not just that which is shown to be true,
but also for which it may be used, who brings it up and for what purpose, i.e. the context. ..
As scientists we are only too acutely aware that we can completely alter its meaning,
indeed we can stand it on its head and thus turn truth into a lie and vice versa.
I hope I need not say any more — we're not little children, after all.
– Or are we? – No, we're not .. .
There you are, then! Who's feeding the pigeons today?
– I am... – Splendid.
Hi.
Hello there, friends! Please, prepare the seat.
I can ’t see Vilma.
I asked the same question. I understand she's had to go to the dentist.
– Did you sleep well? – Very well.
As you all know, we have a difficult task before us today.
That's just what I told our colleagues just now, Director !
We all know what is at stake, so you'll forgive me if I dispense with the preliminaries...
Sorry to be late, Director — I had an appointment with my dentist this morning, and just imagine...
Yes, I've heard. Sit down.
Where was I?
You were saying that we'll forgive you if you dispense with the preliminaries .
Oh yes. Let us dispense with the preliminaries and come straight to the point.
Dr Foustka...
... if you would be so kind...
– Good. Shall we begin? – By all means.
Well then, dear colleague , can you tell us whether it is true that for some time now...
Now, where was I?
You were asking him if it is true that for some time...
Ah yes. Well then, dear colleague , can you tell us whether it is true that
for some time now you have been engaged in the study of what is known as hermetic literature?
T hat's quite true.
– How long, would you say? – Oh, I can't say exactly.
Approximately, then: six months, a year?
Something like that .. .
How many such books would you say you'd read in that time?
I didn't count them.
Approximately: f ive? t hirty? f ifty?
Maybe fifty...
– Whom did you lend them to? – To no one.
Come, come Dr Foustka, are you trying to tell us that nobody borrowed
these sought-after, rare and today practically unobtainable books?
Your friends must have seen them, surely .. .
I don't invite friends to my place, and I don't lend books as a matter of principle.
All right. Now I must ask you to listen carefully, this is a most important question I'm going to ask you :
w hat made you take up this study in the first place?
Why did you start taking such an interest in these things?
I had for some time been disturbed by the increasing interest taken
by young people in everything that had to do with the so-called supernatural.
This unsettling feeling gave rise to the decision to write a brochure in which,
using the example of esotericism — this heterogeneous and tangled conglomerate
originating from various cultural spheres — I attempt to demonstrate the striking contrast
between the various idealistic and mystical teachings of the past
and our current knowledge about the world.
This led finally to my deciding to write a study in which I would set out to show
how diametrically opposed are the various idealistic and mystical beliefs of the past
to our contemporary knowledge of the world.
Sir, that is exactly how we would have expected you to respond to my question.
It does nothing, however, to explain the shocking fact that you yourself allegedly practised magic...
Well, hardly. I let it be known that I was practising it but did very little practising in actual fact...
Why?
It was the only way I could gain the confidence of someone
as distrustful as are today's magicians. ..
I see. Are you saying you desired to be taken into their confidence?
That is interesting, most interesting !
And to what extent, would you say, did you succeed?
To the modest extent, for the time being, of attracting the attention of a certain individual
who has now visited me twice, as you have no doubt been informed.
Did that individual tell you why he visited you?
He said he knew that I was interested in magical practices and that he was willing to initiate me in them.
And you accepted?
No, not in so many words — on the other hand I didn't explicitly turn him down.
What is he asking in return?
That I should, if need be, confirm that he has put himself at the disposal of science...
Did you hear that, Director! Very clever, I must say...
I think the time has come , dear colleague, to pose our crucial question:
how do you explain that, on the one hand, you claim to have a scientific view of the world ,
therefore know that anyone pretending to be a magician is a charlatan,
and yet, on the other, here you are trying to gain the confidence of magicians
and when one of them actually seeks you out, you not only don't scorn him
and throw him out, you actually intend to collaborate with him.
Indeed perhaps even shield him?
This may seem naive to you, but I simply felt, right from the outset,
that I must not confine my efforts to help those who are being led astray by these charlatans
and my intention to do something effective about it
to mere theorising and propaganda.
I simply felt that having taken the first step, it was up to me to continue the journey,
and that it was my duty as a citizen to place my theoretical knowledge
at the disposal of the campaign to unmask and bring to book the perpetrators of these activities.
At the Institute we are all the time professing to be fighting against pseudo-science,
mysticism and superstition — and yet we would be hard put
to it to point a finger at even one of those who spread these poisons.
And not just us — it is nothing short of amazing how little is known
about these matters, how unsuccessful all the attempts to infiltrate these murky waters.
No wonder then that the disease is spreading so rapidly.
That is why I decided to gain the confidence of these people, penetrate their circle
and collect damning evidence at the very source. In short, I've decided
to be an inconspicuous, lone soldier in this — how shall I put it?
in this secret war, having come to the conclusion that my expertise
makes me particularly suitable for this task...
You mean to say that you... that... well, I…
Well, I cannot deny that it would be a bring off some such successful coup.
Dr Foustka is doubtless right when he says that
no propaganda brochures ever won a war...
Am I to understand then that you would be willing to provide us with a record
of any and every meeting you might have, either with this individual of yours or with anyone else?
But of course — that's why I've got into this in the first place...
Tell me one thing, though — why is it that this commendable initiative
of yours has only come to our notice now?
Why did you not inform us about your intentions?
T hat was a mistake.
As you know, we scientists tend to work on our own, we are not in the habit
of reporting every step, and I thought it would be time enough to report progress
when I had actually achieved something worthy of reporting.
It just did not occur to me that a tit-bit of information from an uninformed source
could possibly shake the confidence I had in her to enjoyed at the Institute.
That is hardly surprising, wouldn't you say?
However noble your idea, what you have done is so out of the ordinary and,
if I may say so, so unexpected in your particular case that we cannot be blamed
if at first we misunderstood your motives.
That is hardly surprising, wouldn't you say? How cunning they are!
But never mind — let us not waste any more time.
You have convinced me that it was just a misunderstanding, and all that remains
to be said is that I am glad that it has now been satisfactorily cleared up.
Needless to say, I appreciate what you are trying to do and I shall see to it
that your remarkable initiative is suitably rewarded — particularly once you get into the habit
of keeping a record of your researches and regularly passing it on tous.
Any questions, anyone?
Nothing? In that case, let me spring my little surprise:
tomorrow's social in the Institute garden will be in fancy dress!
Fabulous!
– What a marvellous idea! – Isn't it. I quite agree...
What theme will it have?
Obviously — Witches' Sabbath!
A congregation of devils, witches, magicians and sorcerers. We'll do it in style !
Originally I had thought of it simply' as an attempt to enliven
our tradition of Institute socials by the addition of a parodic element.
Now, however, I see that, thanks to the coincidence of Dr Foustka's revelations,
there is also another way of looking at it:
as a light-hearted tribute to his admirable efforts.
But never mind. Perhaps we can consider this to be a bit of light relief
after our serious session, which has been so satisfactorily concluded !
That's what good friends are for
To bring back the long lost dreams And return them to you on a beautiful day
That's what good friends are fo r
To recall the joy that slipped away And warm your heart on a cold night
Vil d a! Whose turn is it to feed the pigeons?
– Mine ! – Splendid!
Once you let him in I'm sure he'd expect a little more than a kiss on the cheek!
At the very least he'd want to dance with you.
Henry, please leave it alone. After all, I don't give you the third degree —
even though I have more reason than you.
No, no no…. Put it down there!
– What is it? – Somehow I don't feel like it today.
– Does it excite you too much? – No, it's not that.
– So what's wrong? – As if you didn't know.
But I don't!
You don't, do you? And who was it who ratted on me,
telling the Director that the magician had come to see me?
For heaven's sake, Henry, you don't really think...
No one else at the Institute knew about it !
Are you crazy? Why should I do a thing like that?
Quite apart from insulting me by believing for a moment that I would be
capable of denouncing anybody to that idiot, how can you think that I would inform on you?
I would as soon go and inform on myself!
What possible reason would I suddenly have to try and destroy you?
And with you, to destroy myself — our relationship — our life together —
our make-believe jealousy — our love, which you have recently confirmed so deliciously by exhibiting real jealousy —
our memories of all the sunny moments of pure happiness we have known together...
Why, it would be sheer madness!
What do I know about women?
Perhaps you wanted to take revenge on me because of Ma rgaret —
or you were simply scared of that invalid and thought that in this way you could
extricate me from what you considered his clutches...
Come on now, Vilma... I didn't mean it…
It was just a joke...
I thought I'd add a new twist to our game...
Don't touch me! Go away!
Really, Vilma , w hy're you making such a fuss?
You've often asked me to say far worse things to you...
That was different. Do you realise what you've done?
You've accused me in so many words of spying on you!
Kindly get dressed and go away
and don't ever try to patch up what you've just so brutally destroyed !
Are you serious?
Let's end it here and now. It would have come to that sooner or later...
You mean on account of that dancer?
No...
– Why then? – I've lost my respect for you. ..
Well, that's a new one on me.
Today, if you must know, at the Institute —
it struck me then, when I saw how shamelessly you got yourself out of a h ole.
In front of everybody, to offer the Director that you'd act as a stool-pigeon for him ?
And now, to top it all, you come and accuse me of acting like one!
Can't you see how absurd it all is? What's got into you?
Can this really be you I'm talking to? Or has some devil truly possessed you?
That wretched fellow has addled your brain, I expect.
Heaven knows what he did to you, what kind of magic he's trying out on you.
No magic tricks, he is merely helping me to know myself better and to counter
the bad things that lie dormant inside me.
Moreover, my acting as a stool-pigeon, as you put it, not only served
to save me but also to help him — the only way I could !
If they know that I'm in control, they'll leave him alone.
And finally, how could I keep my suspicion that you gave me away to myself —
what kind of a relationship would that be?
You might have done it inadvertently, perhaps to someone whom you trusted
or in the hearing of someone whose presence you were unaware of.
I said nothing to nobody, inadvertently or otherwise, and it's not your expressing
your suspicion that I object to — even though you did it so brutally
and are now, belatedly, trying to wriggle out of it —
what I mind is that you could even think such a thing.
If you can do that, even for a minute, then I don't see how we can stay together.
What an idiot I was to say anything.
But then, I always manage to mess things up .
What am I going to do without you? What's the use of living, if I'm to lose you?
I would like to sink into the ground in shame...
Now you're going to be sorry for yourself, are you?
Do you remember what we said to each other that day by the river under the elms?
It'll do you no good to remind me.
You've hurt me too much for you to talk your way out of it by dragging in our memories.
And anyway, I asked you something…
– You mean to g o? – Exactly!
I know what it is — you're expecting the dancer, aren't you?
I'm not expecting anybody — I just want to be alone !
You're lying, you whore!
Help!
Sorry to show up so late. I only wanted to give you...
Thanks. Do come in, and stay a while .
He's not well... You know, I'm afraid that...
– Is it his heart? – Probably.
Why don't we dance a little?
What do you say? Maybe it will cheer him up.
– Who is it? – It's only me, Doctor.
Come in, Mrs Houbova !
What a mess! It needs to be aired out. You have a visitor.
Have I? Who is it?
You know, the one who...
– Smells? – That's him.
Tell him to come in. Well, what is it?
– I don't know how... – What is the matter?
Look h ere, Doctor, I'm just an ignorant woman...
... I know it's not my place to give you advice...
W hat is it you want to tell me?
I know it's none of my business, but if I were you, I wouldn't trust him !
I can't explain... and I don't know why he comes here in the first place,
but he… ... well, he gives me the creeps...
You let him in readily enough last time.
Be cause I was afraid of him.
Well, I know he looks somewhat odd, but he is quite harmless, you know ,
o r, more precisely, he's too insignificant to be in a position to do too much damage !
I don't know why you have to hobnob with such as h im. A gentleman like you ?!
Mrs Houbovs, I'm over eighteen and perfectly capable of looking after myself.
I'm afraid for your sake. And is it surprising —
why, I remember you as a little three-year-old, me not having children of my own...
Yes, yes, I know. Thank you for your concern —
you must not think I don't appreciate it, but in this case you really need have no fear.
Just let him in and stop worrying.
You're to go in .
– Well? – Well, what?
I'm waiting for you to start your usual litany.
– What're you talking about? – Telling me to get out and so on…
Now, listen. Firstly, I've realized that there's no way I can be rid of you,
and that therefore it's a waste of time and effort to try.
Secondly, without in any way overestimating your so-called stimulating influence,
I have come to the conclusion that the time spent with you does not have to be entirely wasted.
If I have to serve you for your purposes, there is no reason why you
should not reciprocate by serving mine in return.
Did you not at the outset offer to initiate me into your mysteries if I agreed to shield you?
Well, I accept your offer.
Yes, I knew you would in the end …
which explains why I was so persistent.
How nice to see my persistence rewarded at last.
But let me not overdo the modesty — I don't ascribe your decision to my persistence alone,
but also to the undoubted success of our collaboration...
What success do you have in mind?
Well, not only have you managed to keep your job at the Institute,
you have actually strengthened your position there.
If by that you mean that I've jettisoned all my moral principles and left myself open
to whatever you may choose to awaken in me, then you are very much mistaken.
I have not changed, I have only gained a little more self-control.
– What's so funny? – May I be absolutely frank?
– Be my guest. – You are!
You're laughing at me, is that it? Of all the bloody cheek!
Look here, Doctor. There's nothing wrong with you saving your skin by dint of a little skulduggery —
after all, that's precisely the procedure that Haajah and I…
Who?
Haajah, the spirit of politics. We prompted you to act as you did.
But you shouldn't have forgotten the rules of the game.
Rules? What game? What the devil are you talking about?
Does it not occur to you that, like everything else, our collaboration also has its rules?
Do away with your scruples as much as you like —
you know that I'm all in favour of that.
But you really shouldn't try and cheat the one who is guiding you on this exciting,
I might perhaps say revolutionary, path. Revolution, too, has its rules.
Last time you called me a devil. Just imagine for a moment that I really am one !
How do you think I'd react to your amateurish attempt to fool me?
Fool you? But I wasn't...
Look, even if we didn't explicitly promise, surely it should have been obvious
that we would not mention our collaboration to anyone,
much less write official reports about it for those in authority who take a negative view of it.
You have read enough books on the subject to know that even in my sphere
there are limits that cannot be ignored.
You should also know that here, where the stakes are so high,
the inviolability of these boundaries is even more of a legal requirement;
it is not even a law anymore, it is a commandment!
Surely you must realise that, being able to play with the entire world,
we have to put our trust in contacts that simply cannot be trifled with.
As for H im, he loads man with a multitude of unrealistic commandments,
and so he has no alternative but to forgive, from time to time.
Others, on the contrary, liberate man from all these impossible commandments,
and as a result of course they do not have the need,
the opportunity, and in the last instance the they could scarcely forgive someone
who goes back on the agreement that opens up all this boundless freedom.
Their entire world would collapse, were they to do that !
The truth of the matter is, that only by undertaking to be faithful to the authority
that gives us this freedom can we expect to be freed from all undertakings.
Do you follow my drift?
Yes, I understand everything you're saying, but I fear that you fail to understand me.
You don't say !
The undertaking you are obviously referring to can only be considered
as an attempt at treachery on my part by someone who is unaware of the reason
why I was able to give it with a clear conscience.
You did it to save your skin...
Yes, of course, but what would that have been worth had it been paid for by treachery?
Do you take me for an idiot?
I could give that undertaking only because I had made up my mind from the start
not only not to keep it, but at the same time to make the best use of the position
I have gained with its help — naturally in close consultation with you,
in the spirit of our agreement and for our benefit.
In other words, I am now in a position to know exactly what the other side is up to
and to flood them with our disinformation;
I can cover our tracks and provide them with false ones; and I can use all this
to help those of us who are in danger
and sink those who endanger us.
I can serve our cause like an agent planted in the very midst of the enemy,
indeed, at the head of the very department whose job it is' to wage war against us.
I am surprised and disappointed that you have failed to grasp and appreciate my intentions.
Even though you may well have invented this explanation— so be it, I accept it t o give you your last chance .
We, too, can occasionally forgive and offer the culprit the opportunity to reform.
If a little while ago I told you otherwise, then that was only to scare you and coax you
to make this quite unambiguous offer, thus saving you from the very edge of the precipice.
As you can see, I really am not the devil — luckily for you:
the piece of treachery you have been able to get away with in my case would have cost you dear if I were…
Man, your temperature must be a hundred below!
Not quite...
Do you know if the Director is here yet?
No, I don't.
– Have you seen Petruska? – She's not been here...
Where are you thinking of putting it? Somewhere here?
Seems to me the summer-house would be the best place...
Yes, I think you're right. For safety reasons, if nothing else...
I'll light it in the gardener's shed and then carry it over.
It takes a few minutes to get going. ..
I'll put it in the summer-house and a minute or two later — whoosh!
– Oh, Director... – Yes, my dear colleague ?
– Have you got a minute? – Sorry, my friend, but not just now.
– Having a good time? – As you can see...
– Have you seen Petruska? – She's not been here...
How do I know the right moment has come?
Oh, just pick your own time. Or I'll give you a sign...
– I have other things on my mind right now... – What is it?
Can you guarantee that nothing will go wrong?
What could go wrong?
Well, can't something catch fire, or someone might suffocate.
No, don't worry.
– Oh, Director... – What is it, Doctor?
I'm sorry, I know you have a lot of other things on your mind, but this won't take a minute,
and I’m sure, you’ll be interested in it…
No, really, not just now...
And will he not come again? And will he not come again?
He never will come again His beard was as white as snow ...
All flaxen was his poll. He is gone, he is gone ...
And we cast away moan. God ’a mercy on his soul.
Ma rgaret !
Where is the handsome Prince of Denmark?
What are you doing here? Have you run away?
Please tell him, if you see him, that it cannot all be happening of its own accord,
there has to a more profound will at work,
willing our existence, the world, all nature...
Ma rgaret , don't you recognise me? It's me, Henry...
Or does it not strike you as if the cosmos had actually determined to see itself one day through our eyes
and to put the questions which we are now putting, with our lips?
Do go back, Ma rgaret , they will help you get better... everything will be all right again... you'll see...
How should I your true love know From another one?
At the very least, I'm sure he wanted to dance with you...
Please leave it alone! Can't you find something more interesting to talk about?
Did he or didn't he?
All right, if you must know, he did. And that's all I'm going to say.
– Oh, Director... – Yes, what is it, dear colleague ?
– Ouch! – What's happened, Alois?
– It's nothing... – What's wrong with your ear?
– Have you hurt it? – Did something bite you?
– Oh, Director... – Yes, what is it, dear colleague?
– Have you seen Petruska? – No.
Where have you been, sweetheart?
Oh, Director...
Yes, what is it, dear colleague?
I'm sorry, I know you have a lot of other things on your mind,
but on the other hand... I really must... having learned my lesson,
I want to make sure nothing is neglected... I have made certain discoveries, which I have written down in my report.
Don't bother...
But I thought...
I'm not interested in what you believed, I'm not interested in your piece of paper, I'm not interested in you.
You see, my dear sir, the comedy is over !
I don't understand , what comedy?
I'm afraid you have been too clever by half, and you have badly underestimated us,
taking us for much greater idiots than we really are .
– You still don't understand? – No.
All right, then, I'll give it to you straight.
We of course knew all along what you thought of us,
we knew that you were merely pretending to be loyal
while concealing your true views and interests.
Nevertheless, we decided to give you one last chance and so we pretended
to believe your fairy-tale about working for us undercover, so to speak.
We were curious to see how you would conduct yourself after the scare we gave you,
whether perhaps you might at last see the error of your ways and come to your senses.
You chose to spit at our helping hand, and by so doing you have sealed your fate.
– That's not true! – You know only too well that it is !
C an you prove it?
– Shall we oblige? – I'd say yes ... l et's.
Yes, boss?
What did he tell you yesterday?
He said he would pretend to be working undercover for you, while in fact,
in cahoots with those you're fighting against, sabotaging your intelligence service at every step.
He said, and I quote, that he would be our — that is, their—agent in the very midst of the enemy...
He's lying!
What did you say? Can you repeat that?
I said he was lying !
How dare you? How dare you insinuate that one of my finest external collaborators
and a personal friend of long standing is a liar. Fistula never lies to us!
Just what I was about to say, Director. Fistula never lies to us!
So Fistula was an agent provocateur you sent to test me !
I was a fool not to throw him out straightaway. ..
Vilma, I apologise for my stupid suspicions, thanks to which I have lost you !
Mrs Houbova, my apologies to you, too — of course you were right all along...
– Who's he talking to? – That's his landlady, boss.
You're not the only one I've had to investigate, you know.
Everyone comes under my scrutiny, and you'd be surprised how long it sometimes takes
as opposed to your trivial case — before I can get to the bottom of things.
So I fell into your trap, after all, didn't I.
I'm sorry, Doctor... He still has his title, does he?
Oh, fuck all that...
Well, I'm sorry, Doctor, but here you go again — simplifying everything.
Did I not throughout let you know — by dropping various hints as well as quite explicitly
— that you had a range of choices and that you alone could decide your fate?
You did not fall into any trap of mine, you came a cropper thanks to your own pride,
which led you to believe that you could play both ends against the middle and get away with it.
Have you forgotten the pains I took to explain to you
that man has to respect someone in authority — whoever that someone may be — unless he wants to come to a bad end?
And that even revolution has its rules? I really cannot see how I could have made things any clearer to you !
So my conscience is clear.
I did what I could. I'm afraid it's your funeral if you failed to understand...
As always, Fistula is absolutely right. You simply cannot serve all masters,
and at the same time deceive them all. You can't just take and give nothing in return !
Every one of us has to decide where he stands !
Just what I was about to say, Director ! Every one of us has to decide where he stands !
Isn't it paradoxical that now when I have finally lost and my knowledge can serve
no purpose, I'm beginning to understand it all !
Fistula is right: I am a conceited idiot who thought he could use the devil without
having to sign his soul away to him. As if the devil could be deceived.
Daddy!
Just hold on there !
I never said that there is such a thing as the devil!
That's as maybe — but I'm saying it. And he's right here among us!
You mean me, of course?
You're just a subordinate little demon !
I know the way your mind works, Foustka, and I see that, through me,
you would like to point an accusing finger at modern science and denounce it
as the true source of all evil. Am I right?
No, you're not. Through you I merely wish to accuse the destructive pride of intolerant,
all-powerful and selfregarding power, which uses science as a handy bow with
which to shoot down everything that might put it in jeopardy, that is,
anything that does not owe its authority to that power.
Is that the legacy you wish to leave the world, Foustka?
Yes!
Somewhat banal, wouldn't you say? Any influencer these days worth his salt
scatters such pearls of wisdom by the wayside.
However, a legacy is a legacy, so let me demonstrate how tolerant I am
— despite what others may think of me — by overlooking my objections and applauding you.